<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Physicall and chymicall vvorks, composed by Geor. Phædro, sirnamed the Great, of Gelleinen; viz. [brace] 1. His physicall and chymicall practise. 2. His physicall and chymicall cure of the plague. 3. His lesser chirurgery. 4. His chymicall fornace. Being the chymicall way and manner of cure of the most difficile and incurable diseases: as also the preparing those secrets; with the elucidation of the characteristicall cœlestiall physick. Selected out of the Germane and Latine language; by the industry of John Andreas Schenckius of Graffenberg, Doctor of Physick.</title>
            <author>Fedro von Rodach, George, fl. 1566.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90637</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1955</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1497_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208635</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867565</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867565</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119881</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90637)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119881)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 192:E1497[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Physicall and chymicall vvorks, composed by Geor. Phædro, sirnamed the Great, of Gelleinen; viz. [brace] 1. His physicall and chymicall practise. 2. His physicall and chymicall cure of the plague. 3. His lesser chirurgery. 4. His chymicall fornace. Being the chymicall way and manner of cure of the most difficile and incurable diseases: as also the preparing those secrets; with the elucidation of the characteristicall cœlestiall physick. Selected out of the Germane and Latine language; by the industry of John Andreas Schenckius of Graffenberg, Doctor of Physick.</title>
                  <author>Fedro von Rodach, George, fl. 1566.</author>
                  <author>Schenckius, Johannes Andreas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 133, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Sheares, at the Bible in St Pauls Churchyard, near the little North doore.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"1. His .. Fornace." bracketed on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August. 5".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chemistry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Physics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119881:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119881:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PHYSICALL AND CHYMICALL VVORKS, Compoſed by <hi>Geor: Phaedro,</hi> ſirnamed the Great, of <hi>Gelleinen;</hi> viz.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>His Phyſicall and Chymicall Practiſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>His Phyſicall and Chymicall cure of the Plague.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>His leſſer Chirurgery.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>His Chymicall Fornace.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Being the Chymicall way and manner of Cure of the moſt difficile and incurable diſeaſes: as alſo the preparing thoſe Secrets; with the Elucidation of the Characteriſticall Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall Phyſick.</p>
            <p>Selected out of the Germane and Latine Language; By the induſtry of <hi>John Andreas Schenckius</hi> of <hi>Graffenberg,</hi> Doctor of Phyſick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Sheares,</hi> at the Bible in St <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard, near the little North doore. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="foreword">
            <pb facs="tcp:119881:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119881:2"/>
            <p>PEruſing thoſe Learned Pieces of <hi>Baſilius Valentinus, Roger Bacon, Iſaac Holland,</hi> and other excellent Learned men, colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by <hi>Peter John Faber,</hi> Dr of Phyſick of <hi>Monſpelier,</hi> and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed together, finding <hi>George Phaedros</hi> Works inſerted amongſt them, I thought it not imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to prefixe the teſtimony of that Learned Phyſitian, Dr <hi>John Faber</hi> concerning him, in his owne words, in the third page of his argument of the whole Worke, in his <hi>Curru Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaii.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119881:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Scripſit</hi> Georgius Phaedro <hi>Tractatum unicum, &amp; doctiſsimum de Theoria, &amp; practica Lapidis ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientùm, &amp; qui eum Tractatum ritè intelliget, verè &amp; certè ſciret, totam artem noſtram. In hoc enim Tractatu quicquid de lapide Sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entum dici poteſt, clariſsimè manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatur, inter Medicos celeberrimos &amp; Philoſophos nominatur, &amp; ipſe Medicus Celebris vocatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. I. B. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119881:3"/>
            <head>To the courteous or candid <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving found among the Books of my Fathers Library, the manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of that Famous Phyſitian, called <hi>George Phaedro,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by his own hand, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> lay hid a long time in darkneſs, as an uſeleſs burthen unto the earth; I thought, that an Art otherwiſe excellent and uſefull, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and defective, unleſſe it be put unto the Practicke: and this is the reaſon why I peruſed and cauſed it to be printed. For it is well knowne, that good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, if kept within the breaſt, are for no good unleſſe they be imparted unto
<pb facs="tcp:119881:4"/>thoſe that have need of them. Thus this Worke lay hid, ſet downe in paper, and collected for that purpoſe, that thoſe which are taken ill might be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and doubtleſſe he in his Calling did doe his beſt he could. Why ſhould we conceive any other, but that that induſtrious and Learned man, <hi>George Phaedro,</hi> my deare Father, hath intended by theſe his Labours nothing elſe, but that they might be for the good of his ſick neighbours and fellow Chriſtians? And that hee in his experimentall knowledge hath found to cure the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed quickly, ſafely, and ſweetly, the ſame medicaments ſhould be commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated unto poſterity? There are ſome men indeed, if they have gotten any ſecrets, they keep them for themſelves, as if they had found ſome rare and new invented Art, and condemne it to a perpetuall ſilence. How envious their mind is to the publick good, is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently knowne: I thought it good to
<pb facs="tcp:119881:4"/>communicate theſe to the Students of Phyſick, that they might ſerve, being publiſhed, for the good of ſuch that are diſeaſed, and be helped thereby. The which to effect the better, theſe here and there ſcattered members I have reduced into one Body, being ſet down by peeces, and conſcribed in a promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous ſtile, (ſome in Latine, the moſt in the German tongue) reduced them into one Language, and brought them into Order, that they might not be tedious unto the Reader. This my ſmal Labour I deſire to be recommended unto all good men, praying to accept it in good part.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Iohn George Schenkius</hi> of <hi>Graffenberg,</hi> Dr of Phyſick.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119881:5"/>
            <p>THe Reader is advertiſed, not to take diſtaſte of the ſtrange ingrediences at the firſt view, which are put into ſome of the Receipts (as when he writeth, take of our Myſterium, of our Liquor, of Ophirizum, of this and of that Eſſence, &amp;c.) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the manner how they are prepared and compoſed, is ſet downe in the little Treatiſe of this Book, called <hi>Furnus Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:119881:5"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of the Cures performed by the ſpeciall good Medicaments of <hi>George Phaedro,</hi> a Famous Phyſitian.</head>
            <list>
               <head>The Chymcall Practicke containeth theſe following Cures.</head>
               <item>THE cure of Agues.</item>
               <item>The cure of the Plague.</item>
               <item>A compoſition of the camphor'd liquor of the Treacle.</item>
               <item>The cure of the Head-ach.</item>
               <item>The cure of Delirium, or diſtractedneſs of the Braine.</item>
               <item>The cure of Epilepſie.</item>
               <item>The ſeverall Gouts cure, as of Apoplexie,</item>
               <item>Palſie, and of the beginnings of any ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractures. <hi>vix.</hi> of the Chollicke, the Iliack, Paſſion, and of other affects, as of the Stupor, Spaſmus, tremor, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>A deſcription of rectified Aquavitae.</item>
               <item>A ſingular remedy for the Cramp.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:119881:6"/>
               <item>To cure any theume or defluxion of any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</item>
               <item>The true way to make the Panchimagogum.</item>
               <item>To cure all manner of defects of the eyes.</item>
               <item>To cure deafneſſe.</item>
               <item>To reſtore a lively colour to the face.</item>
               <item>To purge the bleeding Flux.</item>
               <item>To cure the Tooth Ague.</item>
               <item>To cure the ſcurvy or foulneſſe of teeth.</item>
               <item>To cure the Squiney.</item>
               <item>To cure the Hidgecock (phlegmon of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aphragme.)</item>
               <item>The cure of the Gout.</item>
               <item>An unguent for the diſſolving of old tartare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Knots.</item>
               <item>To cure ſleepineſſe or Lethargy.</item>
               <item>To cure the conſumption of the Lungs.</item>
               <item>To cure ſhortneſſe of breath.</item>
               <item>To cure the ſtoppage of the Breaſt.</item>
               <item>To cure the Pleuriſie.</item>
               <item>To rectify an ill digeſting Stomack.</item>
               <item>To cure the Spleen.</item>
               <item>To cure the Dropſie.</item>
               <item>To cure the Iaundiſe.</item>
               <item>to cure the burning of the throat.</item>
               <item>To ſtay Vomiting.</item>
               <item>To cure the ſtone Colicke.</item>
               <item>To cure the conſtipation or the ſtones of the entrals.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:119881:6"/>
               <item>To cure a looſeneſſe.</item>
               <item>To expell worms.</item>
               <item>To cure the Emrods before and behind, and the dry chaps in hands and feet.</item>
               <item>To cure the itching unto copulation in Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</item>
               <item>To cure the Impoſthumes of the reines and of the bladder.</item>
               <item>To cure the gravell or ſtone.</item>
               <item>To cure the Carcinoma of the Matrix.</item>
               <item>To expell the falſe conception.</item>
               <item>To cure the Ruptures.</item>
               <item>To cure the ſuffocation of the Mother.</item>
               <item>To cure the Hyſtericall affects; the ſuppreſſion of the monethly courſes, and their immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate running, and of the whites.</item>
               <item>The compoſition of the uterine Elixer.</item>
               <item>To cure barrenneſſe.</item>
               <item>To cure the venereall diſeaſe.</item>
               <item>To mend baldneſſe.</item>
               <item>To cure an exulceration in the throat.</item>
               <item>To firme teeth that are looſe.</item>
               <item>To cure a virulent running of the Reines.</item>
               <item>To cure botches about the privy Members.</item>
               <item>To cure Leproſie.</item>
               <item>To cure an ill coloured skin, overunning the face, and to get off ſome naſtineſs of the hair.</item>
               <item>To cure the ſcabs.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:119881:7"/>
               <item>To cure the Cramp.</item>
               <item>To cure venemous contagious ſymptomes.</item>
               <item>The curing of St <hi>Antonies</hi> fire.</item>
               <item>To cure imposthumes.</item>
               <item>To cure ulcers.</item>
               <item>To heale contumacious Ulcers, which will not ſhut, by reaſon of a wild or rotten fleſh, and other defects.</item>
               <item>To cure a wound.</item>
               <item>A vulnerary unguent.</item>
               <item>A proper oyle for wounds.</item>
               <item>A proper Balſame for wounds.</item>
               <item>A Medico-chymicall cure of the falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>A cure of the Plague of Galenicall and Chymicall materials, containing. theſe following.</head>
               <item>PRophylacticum, or a defenſive againſt the Plague.</item>
               <item>A potion againſt the Plague.</item>
               <item>An Electuary for the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt.</item>
               <item>A Balſame for the Plague.</item>
               <item>The Coeleſtiall treacle againſt all kinds of poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</item>
               <item>The olympick or wonderfull plaiſter.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:119881:7"/>
            <list>
               <head>In the leſser Surgery the following things are to be noted, beſides the noble ſcope of curing.</head>
               <item>THree ſorts of open ſores, and their Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call cure.</item>
               <item>The firſt is ſuch, how it is cured.</item>
               <item>The ſecond is ſuch, how its cure is.</item>
               <item>The third is ſuch, and the manner of its cure.</item>
               <item>A vulnerary decoction.</item>
               <item>A vulnerary Wine.</item>
               <item>The eſſence of Imperatoria.</item>
               <item>The ſecret of oculi Cancrorum.</item>
               <item>The eſſence of the myſtery of Tartar.</item>
               <item>How the heavenly cure ought to be divided.</item>
               <item>An explication of the Specifick cure.</item>
               <item>The quality of Hypericon.</item>
               <item>The vertue of red Corals, and of the blood of pickrels.</item>
               <item>The vertue of Sydericum.</item>
               <item>The operation of a ſilver money made of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury.</item>
               <item>The effects of the great Comfry, of March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mallows, of Mercurialis, and of Chameleon the blacke.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:119881:8"/>
            <list>
               <head>In the Treatiſe of the Chymicall Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace theſe ſecrets are contained.</head>
               <item>THE liquor of Gold.</item>
               <item>The eſſence of Wine and of Herbas, whereof Aquavitae's are made.</item>
               <item>The liquor of Ophirizum.</item>
               <item>The oyle of Pearies.</item>
               <item>The tincture of Corals.</item>
               <item>The eſſence of Antimony.</item>
               <item>The ſecret of the Quinteſſence.</item>
               <item>Of Mercurius dulcis.</item>
               <item>Of the ſpirit of Vitriol.</item>
               <item>Of Tartar.</item>
               <item>Of the philoſophick ſalts.</item>
               <item>Of the extract of Satyrium.</item>
               <item>Of Mumia.</item>
               <item>Of the Hermaphrodite.</item>
               <item>Of the preparation of ſal gemmae, and if the water of Salt.</item>
               <item>Of the eſſence of Sol ſpirit of Wine.</item>
               <item>Of ſalt of Wine.</item>
               <item>Of alcoliſated Spirit of Wine.</item>
               <item>Of the eſſence and forme of wines.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:119881:8"/>
               <item>The manner of drawing the eſſence from hearbes.</item>
               <item>Of the diaphoretick gold.</item>
               <item>Of the preparation of Mumia.</item>
               <item>Of the Turbith Minerall.</item>
               <item>Of the Alchool of Wine.</item>
               <item>Of the oyle of Gold.</item>
               <item>Of the diaphoretick Spirit of Tartar.</item>
               <item>Of the oyle of Saturne and of its ſal.</item>
               <item>Of the eſſence of Antimony.</item>
               <item>The uſe of the eſſence or tincture of Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> his <hi>Laudanum Opiatum</hi> which he made uſe of as a ſpecificum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Agues, found among the ſecrets of <hi>Phaedro.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The oyle of Arſenick and its uſe.</item>
               <item>Butter of Sol for the Aeſchara.</item>
               <item>Praecipitated Aquila.</item>
               <item>The purging of Sal Armonick.</item>
               <item>Aquafort.</item>
               <item>The rectifying of Aquafort.</item>
               <item>The purging of Mercury.</item>
               <item>The purging of Antimony.</item>
               <item>The redneſſe of Antimony.</item>
               <item>Oyle of wax is inſtead of a Balſame for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of wounds.</item>
               <item>Diſſolved Unicorne.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:119881:9"/>
               <item>The Philoſophers Acetum.</item>
               <item>Narcotick and diaphoretick Antimony.</item>
               <item>Of Tartar.</item>
               <item>Of the uſe of Tartar.</item>
               <item>Of the liquor of Tartar.</item>
               <item>Of the oyle of Dwarfe-Elder.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119881:9"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE Medico-Chymicall Practiſe OF <hi>GEORGE PHAEDRO,</hi> A famous Phyſitian.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Cure of Agues.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REceive</hi> Aloes Succocitrine, <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i, of red Myrrhe, of Engliſh Saffron ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i, of our Myſterium gr. iii. Make hereof Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall pills N. 15, with the juyce or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Wormwood; let the Patient take three of them before the Paroxiſme, for the eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuating of the vitious matter of the Ague, which in ſome part being largely and farre
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119881:10"/>ſpread, ſeemeth to have poſſeſt or taken the whole body.</p>
                  <p>But if that deſtroying Diſeaſe is gotten into the broyling bloud of the Veines and Arteries, then Phlebotomize the partie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fit, breathing the Baſilik Veine, or rather the Cephalick, which is more ſafe, or let the Patient be ſcarified, applying Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Glaſſes: our Myſterium is as any of the Univerſals, as the tincture of Sol, of Corals, Pearles, Eſſence of Antimonie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The cure of the Plague.</head>
                  <p>R. Of the liquor of camphorated Treacle <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i ſ. oile of Pearl, gr. vi. of red Corals ℈ i. of Turpentine gut. iii. of Juniper berries-oyle, gut. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>. of the eſſence of Celandine, <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of the waters of the root of Coltsfoot, of Eringo, ana ℥ i. of the flowers of Elder, of Hearts-eaſe, ana ℥ ſ. of red Wine which is very ſweet <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii ſ. of our Myſterium gr. 1. Make hereof a Diaphoretick potion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119881:10"/>
                  <head>The liquor of Camphorated Treacle it made thus:</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of Treacle ℥ ii ſ. of red Myrrh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> x. of orientall Saffron <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of diſtill'd wine ℥ v. Let theſe be diſtill'd according to Art.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Cure of the Head-ach.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of Arſmart growing about Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages M. ii ſ. of Mouſe-eare, of Betony, ana M. ſ: of Sengreen M i. of Night-ſhade M i ſ. of Roſe-water a ſufficient quantity. Let theſe be boiled together, and let there be added to it, of red Corals <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of prepared Pearles ℈ ſ. Make of it a Cataplaſme, apply it to the head ſo long, till all the paine be allayed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Recip.</hi> Of Arſmart M i. Of Mouſe-eat M ſ. Let theſe be boiled in ℥ x. of Betony-water, let one moity boile away, let it be ſtrained, and preſt out.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Recip.</hi> Of this ſtrained liquor ℥ v. of the oyle of Juniper Berrics, gut. v. of our My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterium, gr. i. Make a Potion of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119881:11"/>
                  <head>The Cure of Madneſſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Recip.</hi> Of our Myſterium gr. i. of recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Aqua vitae gut. v. of Arſmart ℥ iii. Make a potion of it, which the party muſt uſe ſo long till the madneſſe be gone, and the uſe of reaſon be reſtored.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Cure of Epilepſie, or Convulſion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcipe.</hi> Of our Myſterium gr. i. of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Pearles ℈ ſ. of the uterine Elixir gut. v. of Paeonie-water a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity. Make a Potion of it, which muſt bee gven to the Epileptick party before the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roxiſme; and after the Paroxiſm let the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der part of the head be anointed with a Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame, in which is Oile of Turpentine <abbr>lb</abbr> i. of Stalactic Galban <abbr>lb</abbr> ſ. Gumme of Elemi or of Ivy ℥ iii. Let theſe be diſtilled, throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away the Feces and Phlegme.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Gutta ejuſque ſpecies; the Gout and its kinde.</head>
                  <p>As Apoplexie, Palſie, the contracture of any part, and their beginnings, or the colick
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119881:11"/>paine, Iliack paſſion, and ſuch like Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes; as Numneſs, Cramp, Trembling: the party is to take a Potion as well at the entring into the Bath, as at the comming forth of it; in which Potion is, of our recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Aqua vitae gr. v. of Dracunculus Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanus ℥ ſ. of our Myſterium gr. i. ſ. make a a Potion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Rectified Aqua vitae.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcipe</hi> Of the juyce of Dracunculus Auguſtanus, of Baulme, of Celandine, of both Snees-worts ana <abbr>lb</abbr> i. Of all kinds of Pepper ℥ i. of Cloves ℥ ii. of Cubebs, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ana ℥ i. ſs. of Cinamon ℥ ii. of Mace ℥ i ſ. of myrrhe ℥ ii. of Bean-aſhes ℥ v, of honey-water ℥ vi. of rectified diſtilled wine <abbr>lb</abbr> v. Let theſe bee infuſed for nine dayes, and ſeparated in a Pellican, unto the Spirits: then take this diſtilled liquor.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Recip.</hi> Of Roſes, flowers of Roſemary, of Sage, of Hearts-eaſe, of Marjoram, of Verbaſcum (Mugwort) ana ℥ ſ. of Zedoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, of the beſt Cinamom ℥ ii. of Mace, of Nutmegs ana ℥ i ſ. of Cloves ℥ ii. of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebs ℥ i. of Amome <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Paradiſe-graines <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> vi. of Civet <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of Amber <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Meſech
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119881:12"/>gr. vi. Macerate them in Aſhes for three dayes, ſeparate, and keep the diſtilled li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor in a glaſs well ſtopped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The following Balſam muſt be continued for a moneth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Recip.</hi> Of the root of Swallow-wort <abbr>lb</abbr> ii. of ground-Dwarfe (Danewort) <abbr>lb</abbr> i ſ. of Gentian <abbr>lb</abbr> i. of red Fearn ℥ iiij. The Herbe of Dracunculus Auguſtanus, of Baulme, of Celendine ana M. ii. of Laven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, of Arſeſmart, of Eupatorium, of Arthri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Ivy ana M. iiij. of Perwinckle M ij. of Flammula, of red Rocket ana M. ij. ſ. of the Flowers of the Lillies of the valley, of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momil, of Verbaſcum, of the leſſer Cento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, of Prunella, of Betony ana M. j. of Hemp-ſeeds <abbr>
                        <hi>lb</hi>
                     </abbr> ſ. of Poppy ℥ i. Of the Celeſtiall water, or of our Indicum, a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient quantity: after the Bath let the affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Members be anointed with the following Unguent.</p>
                  <p>Of Opopanax <abbr>
                        <hi>lb</hi>
                     </abbr> ſ. of Galbanum <abbr>
                        <hi>lb</hi>
                     </abbr> i. of Sagapenum ℥ iiij. of Ammoniack ℥ ii. of Bdellium ℥ i. Let theſe be diſſolved in Vinegar, ſtrained, and an oyle of it diſtilled according to Art; adde thereunto of Oyle of Turpentine <abbr>lb</abbr> i. ſ. of the Philoſophick oile ℥ iiii. of the oyle of Bayes, of Juniper
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119881:12"/>ana lib. ſ. of Spick ℥ i. of Cantharides ℥ v. of both ſorts of Pepper ℥ iiij. of Cardamom ℥ ij. of freſh Caſtoreum ℥ iij. of Euphorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ℥ ij ſ. of Maſtix, Frankincenſe ana ℥ iiij. of Myrrhe lib. ſ. Let theſe be diſtilled in the manner of an oyle, adde thereunto of liquid Storax ℥ i. ſ. of the ſpawn of Frogs, of Frogs gendred in leaves num. xx. of earth-wormes, of the greaſe of a Badger, of a Fox, of a Wild-Cat, of a Bear, ana ℥ iij. of Deer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuet, or of a Stag ℥ iiij. of Barrowes greaſe ℥ ii. of the beſt Vinegar, and of diſtilled Wine ana ℥ i, ſ. Diſtill theſe againe: let the following Fomentation be uſed, either in ſtead of a Bath or of an Unguent.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the greaſe of a Badger, of Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitium of Frogs, of oyle of Olives lib. ſ. of Juniper <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> v. of Maſtix, of Myrrhe, ana lib. ſ. of Salt ℥ ij. of Turpentine ℥ vi. Mingle theſe, burne them well in a kettle, lay the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected member over it, ſtaying it with a convenient inſtrument, let it be well cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, leſt the vapours goe away, doing no good: if the Fomentation cooleth, heat it againe; this muſt be continued for twelve hours everyday. Thus the juyce of Flammula being diſtill'd, and taken mornings and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, will in a ſhort time cure that ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119881:13"/>
                  <head>This following Receipt is good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Cramp.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the Oſſicula cut in the midſt of white Snailes, of Hares-knuckles ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ij. of prepared red Corals ℥ ſ. mingle theſe:</p>
                  <p>℞. Of this powder <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of our Myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um gr. 1. Water of the Ocymus Garyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyllatus ℥ iij. Make a Potion of it, which muſt be often iterated, the Oſſicles (ſhells) muſt be well heated, or made hot in the hand, then the parts tormented with the Cramp will the ſooner be eaſed, and freed from that ſtretching and contraction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of diſtilling Rheumes in Mans body.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of our Panchimagogum, of the great Frankincenſe, of prepared red Corals ana ℈ i. of Chalcantin Sulphur gr. ij. of the juyce of Arſmart, of the whiteſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, ana a ſufficient quantity. Make a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarctick bole of it: or.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of our Panchimagogum, of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petiall Pills, ana ℈ i. of the Species, of precious ſtones, of Diamoſhum ana ℈ ſ. of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119881:13"/>Opium gr. i. Make pills of it with the juyce of Lemons.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Our Panchimagogun is made thus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcipe.</hi> Of Spirit of Wine lib. i. Of Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of <hi>Diambra</hi> ℥ i ſ. Infuſe theſe for fourteen dayes, digeſt it in the Sunne, let the Veſſels be well ſtopt, this ſpirit is ting'd of a deep red: ſhake it every day three or foure times, then caſt off the ſpirits from the Species of Diambra: digeſt it in a Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my for a ſennight or fortnight.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The following things purge the skin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>℞. Of freſh Scammonie ℥ ſ. of the beſt Rhubarb <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iii. ℥ i. of Colocinth <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> v. or ℥ ſ. of the beſt Agarick <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iiii ſ. of Turbith ℥ ſ. of Hermodactils <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. ſ. of the black ſneeze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort ℥ ii. Of Sene leaves ℥ i. of Maſtix, myrrhe, red roſes, of Fennel-ſeeds, of Aniſe ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. ſ. Theſe being grinded and ſteeped, muſt be put in a linnen bagge, and preſt in a pewter Preſſe: diſsolve in this expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, of Aloes Succotrina ℥ xii. at laſt let this Wine evaporate in a Balmy, and a ſpiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the bottome will be left as thick as honey, Of this Compound may be taken halfe a Scruple, or a whole one, in Malmſey,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119881:14"/>or with other pills aggregative. Adde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſome drops of Chalcantin oyle, to ſtrengthen its purging quality.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt all manner of ſymptoms of the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcipe.</hi> Of white Lythargyre, of Alu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men plumoſum, of extinct Tutia, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of waters of Eye-bright, of Speed wel, of Fennell ana ℥ i ſ. of flowers of white Verbena, of Succory, of Cyanus ana ℥ i. of Camphore <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. ſ. Theſe being beaten, diſtill them: with this diſtilled liquor wet a linnen Cloth, and thus cold waſh the eyes with it: The leaves of the Verbana bearing whitiſh flowers, muſt be worne about the neck like a neck-cloth for nine dayes. With or by this Amulet are perfectly cured Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phora, <hi>aliàs</hi> Lachrymae (teares,) opthalmia, or Lippitudo, or rheume in the eye, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſymptomes of the eye. The Pearle in the eye is inſtantly cured, if a piece of the root of Taraxicus belaid on the tongue: or if any humorous matter runneth in the eye, eating and conſuming the white of the eye, is healed, if the clay of Anatolia, ſealed with the hand of the Turkiſh Emperour, or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119881:14"/>in lieu of it, the chalk of Malta, be diſſolv'd in Roſe-water and applyed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The cure of Deafeneſs.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of Earth-worms, of Saws, of each ℥ iii. of an Oxe-Gall ℥ i. ſ. Diſtill it per Alembick. Add thereunto the eſſence of black ſneeze-wort ℈ i. the juyce of Rhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barbe preſt forth with the oyle of bitter Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. ſ. oyle of Camphire <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. ſ. of the ſeeds of Nigella, of Hyoſciamus, of Poppy, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of the water of the flowers of the leſser Centorie <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii ſ. of Celandine ℥ ſ. of Hungariſh Saffron ℈ i.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To reſtore the loſt colour of the face.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the water of the flowers of Roſemary, of the two ſorts of Betony, ana ℥ ii. of the Herbs of Verbena, ℥ iiii. of Wormewood ℥ i. of the root of Polypodium ℥ ii. ſ. of our Myſterium gr. i. Make a large lotion againſt the Nitrous Colours of the face.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119881:15"/>
                  <head>Againſt Bleeding.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the root of whites enicle ℥ ſ. of Hempſeed, of Milke, a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantity: Boil theſe and preſs them out; of that expreſſion ℞. ℥ iiii, of Chalcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thin Sulphur. gr. ii. of our Myſterium gr. i. Make a Potion; outwardly apply to the thighes, if men; but if women, to the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the following hot decoction ſo long till the bleeding be ſtayed.</p>
                  <p>℞. The rindes of the beſt root of Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane ℥ ſ. of Vinegar of Roſes a ſufficient quantity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt Tooth-ache.</head>
                  <p>THe Anodyn Balſam muſt be uſed, or elſe let the teeth be often waſhed with the following warme decoction.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the root of Arſmart M. v. of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanum M. ii. of the ſeeds of Staphiſagria <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. Of Plantaine-ſeeds <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of the rinde of the root of Tamar. ℥ ſ. of Henbane ℥ iii. of the root of Tormentilla <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Roſe-Vinegar <abbr>lb</abbr> i. of red wine <abbr>
                        <hi>lb</hi>
                     </abbr> ii. Let theſe be well boiled: Phlebotomy and Scarification muſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119881:15"/>be uſed alſo: and if it be a hollow tooth which paineth the partie, put into it Frogs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greaſe, that paine will be allayed for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt rottenneſſe of Teeth.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the juyce of Plantayn, or of a decoction made of it with wine, of Celandine, of the golden Comfry, of Dracunculus Auguſtan ana ℥ iii. of Oxymel i. quart. of Aloes ℥ i. ſ. of Alome ℥ ii. Make a Gargariſme, which muſt be uſed daily: if the teeth doeſtink and are growne black, and the gummes are ſwell'd, full of humors, then take the Aſhes of Roſemarie-ſtalkes, put them into a cleane Linnen, wipe them daily with it, continuing it for five or ſix dayes: if thoſe humours returne, then you muſt continue the uſe of this Medicine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt the Squinſie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Jewes-eares, grown on Elders ℥ ſ. Let theſe be ſteeped over night in water of Prunella ℥ v. preſſe it out, adde to it of our Myſterium gr. i. and give to the partie this Potion: Let the party daily gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gariſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119881:16"/>three or foure times with this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing warme Gargariſme.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of Urine of man ℥ i. of the juyce of Hypericon ℥ ii. of Arſemart ℥ iii. of Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nella ℥ i. ſ. of Oxymel Scylliticum lib. ſ. In the interim<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if the parties tongue be furr'd, or the throat be fill'd with clammineſſe, let it be rubb'd with a Scarlet cloth, that it bleed: if any tumor apparent and great paines be accompanied with it, then uſe this Cataplaſme.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of Jewes-Eares ℥ ſ. of the root of Dwarfe-Elder ℥ i. ſ. of Arſeſmart M i. of Roſe-Vinegar, a ſufficient quantity: adde thereto of Camphor ℈ ſ. make a Pultiſe. Let theſe be boiled, and add of our Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium gr. ii. This Decoction is againſt the Inflammation of the throat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt the Heart-groaning of Children.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the leſſer Water-Creſſes M. i. of Wine or Water, a ſufficient quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Let it be boiled, and adde to it of our Myſterium gr. ii. Make a Potion againſt the inflammation of the Breaſt. This decocted Herbe is applyed as a Pultiſe to the place af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:119881:16"/>
                  <head>To cure the Gout.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of Aloes, being waſhed nine times of the Decoction of the midler Cumfry ℥ i. ſ. of our Myſterium gr. xiv. of red Myrrhe, of white Frankincenſe ana ℥ ſ. of red Corals, or in lieu of them, of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Sarda, of tranſparent Citrine
<list>
                        <item>Caribis, ana ℈ ſ.</item>
                        <item>Amber, ana ℈ ſ.</item>
                     </list> Of the beſt Unicorn gr. iiii. of the beſt Moſch gr. ii. of ordinary Saffron. gr. vii. Make a maſſe of Pills with the juyce, or the diſsolved Salt of Arſemart, hereof are made Pills of the bigneſs of <hi>Ruffus</hi> his Peſt-pills, two whereof are miniſtred morning. The midler Solidage or Cumfry being boiled, and the Arſeſmart expreſs'd, muſt be put between two Tiles and covered with Dung, exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally applyed, if the paines be extreame; uſe the Anodyn Ointment heated.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of oyle of Cloves ℥ ii, of Juniper Berries, of Sulphur Chalcantin, ana ℥ i. Theſe muſt be diſtilled <hi>per</hi> Alembick, all Junctures being well luted: adde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</p>
                  <p>Of Tile-Oyle ℥ ii. of Turpentine
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119881:17"/>quar. i. of freſh Caſtoreum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Opium, ana ℥ ſ. of Saffron ℈ ii. Diſtill this againe gently, you have an Anodyn Oyle, wherewith the affected place is anointed: or take a Lythar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyr prepared with Alome and Roſe water <abbr>lb</abbr> i. boile it in water of the Spawn of Cray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſhes, and May-dew, or Rain-water to a thickneſs of honey, adde thereto of the juyce of
<list>
                        <item>Cray-fiſhes, quart i.</item>
                        <item>Gammara, quart i.</item>
                     </list> Of the Herb of Arſeſmart <abbr>lb</abbr> ſ. of Solanum (nightſhade,) of Sempervivum or Houſe-leek, of the flowers of
<list>
                        <item>Water-Lillie, ana ℥ i.</item>
                        <item>Nenuphar, ana ℥ i.</item>
                     </list> Of Henbane boiled ℥ ii ſ. of oyle of Poppy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed ℥ i ſ. Boile theſe againe to a thickneſs, at laſt adde to it of Opium ſteeped in oyle of Bayes, and Juniper, for ſome dayes and ſtrained ℥ vi. of Camphore ℥ i ſ. of Myrrhe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Frankincenſe, ana ℥ ſ. make of it an Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyn Unguent, and it muſt be macerated in a well-ſtopped Glaſs at the heat of the Sun for a Moueth, after the place affected muſt be anointed with it warme.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:119881:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the diſſolving of old tartarous knots and ſtones; the following ointment muſt be applyed daily once or twice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>℞. Of the liquor of Mumia quart i. of the ſweet oyle of chalianthum (vitriol) ℥ i. of the ſpirit rectified of Tartar; mixe theſe; Or;</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the liquor of Mumia quart i. of the oyle of Juniper berries, ℥ x. of Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine. ℥ ij ſs. mix theſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt ſleepineſſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of our Myſterium gr. i. of oyle of Pearles, gr. vi. of boyled Roman cole, ſweetned with the whiteſt Sugar. ℥ ſs. make a bole of it, which muſt frequently b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> uſed or taken.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Agaioſt the rottenneſſe of the Lungs, and ſtinking breath.</head>
                  <p>R <hi>Recip.</hi> Of our Myſterium, gr. i. of oyle of Juniper Berries, gr. v. of the water of the Auguſtan Dragon, ℥ ii. of Arſemart ℥ iii. mixe theſe, and make a potion.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:119881:18"/>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt ſhortneſſe of breath <hi>Aſthma.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of our Myſterium gr. i. of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Sulphur gr. x. of the roote of Elecampane ℥ ſs. a ſufficient quantitie of Honey: make it into an electuarie, let the partie take that whole quantitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Against the oppreſſion of the Cheſt or Breaſt.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the decoction of the Herbe of Cyclamen or Saw bread in Wine, with the Myriſtick Nut ℥ iii. Make a Potion for the ſtreightneſſe of the Breaſt, to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt Pleuriſie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> The juice of Tormentilla <abbr>lb</abbr> ſs. of Carduus water ℥ iii. of wild ſage ℥ ii. of flowers of the Lilies of the Valley, of Bugloſſe, of Violets, of Borage quart. i. of Cinamom ℥iii. of the brain of a Kite qu<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> i. Theſe being mingled, are to be ſteeped for eight dayes, and diſtilled in a Balmy.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of this diſtill'd liquor ℥ i. of our My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterium gr. i ſs. make a potion.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119881:18"/>
                  <p>℞. Of the Herb of Baulm, of cole Mi. of Mint M ſs. of Wormewood P i. Steep theſe in diſtill'd Wine, for twelve houres at a gentle heat.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of this liquor ℥ ſs. of oyle of Juniper Berries, gr. v<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Malmſie ℥ i ſs. or Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phore gr. i ſs. of our Myſterium gr. i. Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle theſe and make a diaphoretick Potion, which the partie is to take mornings and evenings: Outwardly to the affected place uſe this Unguent.</p>
                  <p>℞. of the diſtill'd and expreſs'd oyle of ſweet Almonds, ana ℥ iii. oyle of tiles ℥ i. Mixe theſe, make a ſoft Unguent accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to art, with a quantity of wax.</p>
                  <p>Or; ℞. Of Sallet oyle quart. i. of the juice of Tormentilla ℥ ſs. of the braine of a Kite ℥ i. Wax a lineament; forget not to Phlebotomize the partie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To cure the crudities of the Stomack, and its digeſtion.</head>
                  <p>BEfore dinner and ſupper, let the partie take this Bole.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the oyle of Juniper Berries gut. v. of conſerve of Roſemary flowers ℈ i ſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of our Myſterium gr. i. Make a bole of it.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119881:19"/>After dinner and ſupper let him uſe this powder.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of pulveriſed water mint <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs. of the dry twigs of a haſel-miſleto ℈ ſs. of Oak leaves ℈ i of Galanga <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Sugar a ſuſſicient quantity: make a powder of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt the Spleen.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of Mans Urine <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i ſs. of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Tamarisk ℥ v. of the calcined Lazul ſtone ℈ ſs. of our Myſterium gr. i. make a Potion of it.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of Opopanax, of Galbanum, of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacum, ana ℥ ii. of the rectified bleſſed oyle ℥ i ſs. Make a plaiſter according to art, which muſt lie on the ſcirrous Spleen, for ſix or eight weeks.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt the Dropſie.</head>
                  <p>IN the firſt place, the Dropicall partie being brought to an abſtinence, there muſt be made a continuall Potion, in which are boyled the roots of Aſclepias, or Vince Toxicum, according to our cuſtome, in <abbr>
                        <hi>lb</hi>
                     </abbr> i. of Malmeſie, let it be ſtrained and preſs'd out. In ℥ iii of this decoction, muſt be ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119881:19"/>over night, of our Myſterium gr. i ſ. up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hot embers, adde unto it of Rhubarbe rectified by ſpirit of Tartar ℈ i. of the oyle of Juniper Berries gut. v. of the water of Speedwell ℥ ii. make a Potion, to be taken daily three or foure times, and muſt be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed till the cauſe of the diſeaſe is taken off.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the diſperſing of the humour, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly muſt be applyed to the decoction of</hi> Oedipus.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of Swallow-wort ℥ ii. of the herb of Dwarfe Elder M i. of Mugwort M ii. of the leſſer Water Creſſes M i ſs. of Moſſe grown on ſtones M i. of flowers of Nenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phar, of Verbaſcum, of Hypericon, ana P i. of Elders M i. of Chamomil P i. of ſeeds of radiſh ℥ ſs of Carrowie <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iij. of meal of Beanes ℥ i. of dried Pigeons dung <abbr>lb</abbr> ſs of Goats dung quart. i. of Hens dung ℥ i ſ.</p>
                  <p>Let all theſe be boyled in red Wine, and Roſe water, ſtraine and preſſe it out; dip a linnen cloth into this hot liquor, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to the Tumour, continue it till the humour be gone, and no remainder of it be left. The Patient under the cure may uſe the Electuarie of Diacubebs, prepared thus.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:119881:20"/>
                  <p>℞. Of Crocus Martis reverberated very ſubtilly <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i ſ. of Spodium ℈ v ſ. of all ſorts of Sandals, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i ſ. of the foure cold great ſeeds, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> v. of the ſeeds of Endive, of Purſlane, of Lettice, ana ℈ ij. of Sugar diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in the juice of Pomgranats: make this mixture into an Electuarie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The cure of the yellow Iaundies.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of our Myſterium gr. i. of Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wormes, of dry Saws, ana num. v. of orientall Saffron gr. iij. of diſtill'd Wine, in which is ſteeped Celandine and Centory the leſſer ℥ i ſ. of Malmſie ℥ iij. make a dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoretick drink of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The cure of <hi>Soda</hi> (a heat of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks Orifice.)</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of our Myſterium gr. of waſh'd Aloes <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of Marin Chalk ℈ ſ. of ſeeds of Poppie ℈ ſ. of the oyle of Myriſtick Nuts gr. v. Make Pils of them with the juice of Mint, or of Cyclamen, num. ix. three at a time to be taken.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:119881:20"/>
                  <head>To cure Vomiting.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of Ferment (leven) quart i. of the juice of Mint, expreſt with Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, as much as is ſufficient.</p>
                  <p>Boile theſe to the forme of a plaiſter, which muſt be applyed hot to the Stomack, being cold, renew it hot; and as often the Patient hath eaten or drunk, let that plaiſter lie on the Stomack for one or two houres.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To cure the paine of the Stone Cholick.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the extract of the root of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meleon ℥ ſ. of diſtill'd Sallet oyle, of oyle of Juniper Berries, ana gut. v. of Aniſeeds<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oyle gut. viij. of the water of Arſemart ℥ iii. of our Myſterium gr. i. make a Potion.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of true Zibeth gr. x. of oyle of Mace gr. vi. Mix theſe and anoint the Navill, laying upon it the ſhell of a Walnut for an hour or two. This is an approved reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy alſo againſt the riſing of the mother.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119881:21"/>
                  <head>Againſt the Stone of the Entrals col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led conſtipation</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of our Myſterium gr. v. of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtix, of Mumy, ana ℥ ſ. of Aniſeeds ℥ i. of Diacidonium of deſpumed Hony, or of juice of Lemmons or Quinces, a ſufficient quantity: mix theſe into an Electuarie: the doſe of it is <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To cure a Lask or Looſeneſſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of Plantaine water, or of the decoction of Fern-root, or of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtan Dragon ℥ i ſ. of Camphorated li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor ℥ ſ. of mans Urine <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i ſ. of the oyle of red Corals ℈ i. of Crocus Martis ℈ ſ. of our Myſterium gr. i. Make of it a Potion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt Wormes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of our Myſterium gr. i. of oyle of Turpentine gut. v. of the water of Arſemart ℥ iij. of Wormewood ℥ i. Make a Potion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the Fundament, apply this U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>guent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>℞. the green Herbe of Hypericon, of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119881:21"/>the leſſer Centorie, ana M i. of waſhed Aloes a ſufficient quantity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Make an Unguent according to art.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt the Piles, Emrods about the Womb or Fundament; The chops in the palms of the hands, and ſoales of the feet,</head>
                  <p>CHiefly muſt be taken the Paleſtin Poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, next that, that fomentation muſt be uſed four or five times againſt the Chops.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the root of the leſſer Nettle ℥ vi. of Raponticum, of the regall Cumfry, of Eupatorium, of Pyrola or Wintergreen, of the leſſer Centorie, of Prunell, ana M i. of Barly meal, of Wheat meal, ana ℥ i. of pure water a ſufficient quantitie, for a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction.</p>
                  <p>Or in lieu of it, let the Chops be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed mornings ans evenings with the following unguent.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the greaſe of a wild Cat, of a Hart, of a Badger, of Petroleum, ana ℥ ſs. diſolve or melt theſe in a gentle heat, adde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto of the oyle of Juniper Berries ℥ vi. of tile oyle <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iij. of oyle of Spike <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. mixe theſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:119881:22"/>
                  <head>Againſt Womens Satyrials (or itching) unto Copulation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of roots of Radiſh, of oyle of bitter Almonds, of oyle of Apricocks kernels, ana ℥ i. Make a Peſſarie, leave it over night in the neck of the Womb.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt the exulceration in the Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys and Bladder.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Seaven Winter Cherries, ſteep them in the beſt Wine, or in newly boyled Wine of ℥ ij. for twelve houres, preſſe it out very hard, and adde to this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, of mans Urine <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of oyle of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, gut. v. of white Frankincenſe <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs. of our Myſterium, gr. i. Mixe theſe and make a Potion of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The cure of the Stone.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the root of Acorus (Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Aromaticus) or of Gariophyllida Liliorum Crocorum, of the Herbes of Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenta, of Carduus, ana M. i ſ. of Maiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haire M. ii. of white Ginger <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i ſ. Let theſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119881:22"/>be boiled according to our manner, in <hi>Alſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Wine, ſtraine and expreſſe them, in that expreſſion ſteep for twelve houres, of our Myſterium, gr. ii. adde unto it of the oyl of Juniper Berries, gr. v. of orientall Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, gr. ii. Make a Potion of it, to be uſed three or four times in the Bath. The Bath is this.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of roots and Herbes of white Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neps, of Parſenips, ana <abbr>lb</abbr> i. of Aquilina <abbr>lb</abbr> ſ. of Anonis, of the Herbes of Gramen, of Speedwell, of Fragaria, of Buphtalmus, of Maiden-haire, of Mugwort, of Verbaſcum, of Chamomil, of Ariſpaltea, ana M. i. of Betonie of purple and white flowers, ana M. ii. of Prunella, of Carduus Benedictus, ana M. i. of ſeeds of Mug-wort, of Radiſh, of Nettles, ana ℥ v. of Winter-Cherries, quart i. of Snow-water, or Rain-water, or <hi>May</hi> dew, a ſufficient quantity, which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth inſtead of the Baths in <hi>Helvetia,</hi> the <hi>Alpes</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and muſt be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ten or fourteen days.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:119881:23"/>
                  <head>Againſt the Carcinoma or Canker of the Wombe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the root of the regall Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fry, <abbr>lb</abbr> ſ. of Ariſtolochia rotunda ℥ vi. of the Herbe of Agrimonie, of Sanicle, of the Lyons foot. of Winter green, of both Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winckles, ana M. i. of the Auguſtan Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, M. vii. of Parſenips, of Turneps, ana M. ſ. of new red wine two quarts: Let theſe boyle together, and take of this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor ℥ iij. of the liquor of Microcoſme <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of our Myſterium gr. i. Make a Potion of it.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of Turpentine waſh'd in Roſe water ℥ vi. of Aloes Succotrine ℥ i. of the juice of the great Cumfry-root, of Ariſtolochia rotunda, of the Herbes of Agrimonie, of Winter green, of Plantaine, of the Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan Dragon, of Arſemart, of the flowers of Verbaſcum, of Hypericon, of Prunella, of Centorie the leſſer, of Betonie, ana ℥ ii ſ. of the oyle of Dill, of Frogs, of Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wormes, ana <abbr>lb</abbr> i. Make a Peſsarie, to be put up into the Neck of the Wombe for foure or five houres every day. This may be applyed to the ſciſsures or chops of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119881:23"/>Privities and the fundament, and to the open Piles.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of Harts ſuet <abbr>
                        <hi>lb</hi>
                     </abbr> ſ. of the oyle of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie, of Dill, of yolkes of Egs, ana ℥ vi. of wax a ſufficient quantity. Make an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent for the back: theſe three, <hi>viz.</hi> a Potion, Clyſter and Unguent, muſt be uſed daily.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To expell a Mola (a lump of fleſh</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>RRecip.</hi> Of Baulme-water, of Speed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well-water, of oyle of Juniper Berries gut. v. oyle of Amber gut. iii. of our Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium gr. i. of orientall Saffron gr. iii. of Moſch gr. i. make a Potion.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of Scammonie <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iii. of Lapis Lazu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of Amber <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> vi. of artificiall Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colle <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Auſtrian Saffron ℥ ii. of Opo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panax, a ſufficient quartitie. Let there be made a Peſsarie for the Matrix, which muſt be miniſtred at the firſt opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the drawing forth of the Mola, elſe comming to a perfect bigneſs it may be the death of the Child-bearing Woman.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:119881:24"/>
                  <head>To cure the two ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rts of Ruptures.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the extract of the root of the great Comfry ℥ ſ. of white Sanicle ℥ i. of the Salt of Arſemart <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Swallow-wort ℥ iii. of the oyle of Juniper Berries gut. v. of our Myſterium gr. i. Make a Potion of it, which is good againſt all ſorts of Ruptures: Such Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents muſt avoid contentions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt the riſing of the Mother.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the liquor of Camphorated Treacle <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of the extract of the root of Chameleon ℥ ſ. of the oyle of white Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe ℈ i. of the oyle of Cinamon or of Cloves gut. iii. of the Uterine Elixir gut. v. of the water of Elder flowers <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iii. of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momil ℥ i ſ. of Arſemart. of the Tinctus of the Balſam g. v. of Salt of <hi>Iupiter</hi> ℈ ſ. Make a Potion of it.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:119881:24"/>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of Hyſtericall paſſions, of the obstru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Moneths, or their immoderate purgation, and of the Whites.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the water of Baulm, of Speed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, of Pulegium, ℥ ſ. of Mugwort, of the flowers of white Lillies, of Sanicle, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> vi. of the oyle of Savin-Berries, of Bayes, of Citrin Amber, ana gut. v. of the Uterin Elixir gut. v. of ſalt of Wine ℈ i. of our Myſterium gr. i. of Saffron gr. ii. Make a Potion, let the party drink of it mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and evenings.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Uterine Elixir is made thus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the yellow flowers of Leu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coum, of Roſemary, of Lavender, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> v. of the Herbe of Ocymus, of Garyophil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata, of ſweet Marjoram, of Sage, ana ℥ ſ. of the root of Carnabodium or Deronicum Alex: ℥ i ſ. of Mace, of Nutmegs, of the beſt Cinamon, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Cloves, of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebs, of Maſtix, of Frankincenſe, of Myrrhe, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ.</p>
                  <p>Put ſo much of eſsence of wine to it, that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119881:25"/>it ſtand a hand breadth above it: being ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and well mix'd, diſtill it ſeven times in a Balmy, then temper this diſtill'd liquor with the powder of the leaves of Opiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zum, num. xx. Of Pearles, of red Corals, ana ℥ i. of garnats, Rubies and Sardies, ana ℥ ſ. Digeſt theſe in a Balmy for a moneth, and afterwards ſeperate the oyle from the phlegme.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt Barrenneſſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>RRecip.</hi> Of the extract of the root of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrion Erythronicum ℥ ſ. of the ſalt of balm ℈ i. of the oyle of the ſeeds of the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Nettle, gut. iii. of the liquor of Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon drawn with diſtill'd Wine ℥ i ſ. of the Uterine Elixer gut. v. of our Myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um gr. i. Make a ſmall Potion, which muſt be taken morning and evening.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The cure of the Venereall d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſeaſe.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Patient containe himſelfe in a warm room for two or three daies, and let him uſe this medicament.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of our Myſterium gr. i. of Treacle <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of the Electuarie of the juice of Roſes
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119881:25"/>of Meſ. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of Tramin-Wine ℥ i ſ. Make a Potion of it, which muſt be uſed ſeverall times; or, take of the Treacle water ℥ ſ. of the ſalt of Arſemart <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of our Myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, gr. i. Mix theſe: the Patient having taken this, let him into a tub of hot water, in which is put, of Alome <abbr>lb</abbr> v. of Salt <abbr>lb</abbr> x. Let theſe be mixed, put to it a Cetum Scyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linum, and having ſtood in the aire for three dayes, evaporate it to a dryneſſe, then boyl that in raine water, to the thickneſſe of an oyle, this we call artificiall Thermae or Baths: Adde unto it of the roots of Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-wort ℥ x. of the great Comfry, of Ariſtolochia rotunda, ana quart i. of white Sanicle, or in the lieu of it, Cyclamen (Sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread) ℥ ii ſ. of the Herbe of Centorie the leſſer, of the wild Winter-green, ana M ii. of Celandine M i ſ. of the Yellow Comfry, of Arſemart, ana M iij. of Oak leaves M ii. of tops of Juniper M ii ſ. Make a Bath, which the Patient muſt make uſe of as long, till all the Porkie ſores are gone, and the malignant Ulcers thereof. The Wharts, Boyles, and bones quite rotten, and other ſtubborn ſypmtomes, muſt beſides the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary way of curing of Ulcers, have a Bath made, which is more ſtypifying.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:119881:26"/>
                  <p>℞. Of oyle of Vitrioll ℥ ſ. of water of mans Blood, of Arſeſmart, ana ℥ i ſ. Or ℞. Of oyle of Cloves, of Camphore, made by the white of an eg ℥ i. Mix it, and with this unguent or liquor anoint the places affected, and apply upon them a ſtiptick plaiſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt the falling off of the haires.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of leaves of Wormewood, of Roſemary, of Betonie, of water Mint, of Pulegium, of Abrotanum, ana M i ſ. of Roſes M i. of the root of Aſarabacca <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iii. of the orientall Turbith ℥ ſ. of Cyprus Nuts num. 4. Let theſe be boiled in lees, and ſtrain it, let the parties head be waſht with it, adding Venice ſoap, and drying the head with warm clothes, then anoint the head thus.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of diſtill'd water of Honey, of urine, ana <abbr>lb</abbr> ſ. oyle of Serpents quart i. of Cloves ℥ ii. Mix theſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119881:26"/>
                  <head>For the exulceration of the throat.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the greater Comfry <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii ſ. of of Ariſtolochia rotunda <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> vi. of Winter-green M. i. of St Johns Wort M i. of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nella M i ſ. of Barly P. i. of white Vitriol ℥ ſ. of Sal gemmae <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i ſ. of the male Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, of the beſt Myrrhe, ana ℥ ſ. Boyle theſe in Raine-water to <abbr>lb</abbr> i ſ. ſtraine it, and diſſolve in this ſtrained liquor Oxymel Scyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticum ℥ ix. and make a gargariſme.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For looſe Teeth.</head>
                  <p>ANoint them with the oyle of Crocus Martis, or, ℞. of the oyle of Vitriol, gut. v. of the decoction of Plantain, made of red wine, ℥ i ſ. Mix theſe: But thoſe Teeth that are ready to fall out, let them be anointed with the oyle of Myriſtick Nuts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For the Virulent Gonorrhea.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> of the ſeeds of Purſlane, of Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, of Lettice, of Nightſhade ana ℈ ii. of the four hot ſeeds, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of Crocus
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119881:27"/>Martis very ſubtilly reverberated, of bole Armenic very well calcined, ana ℈ ii. of the beſt Sarda ℈ ii ſ. of Spodium <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii ſ. Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſe that which is to be pulveriſed, add to it the Electuarie of Gemms, a ſufficient quantitie: make a mixture in Ferme of a tincture, or broth, let the partie tak <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of it in the morning, at three of the clock, and at evening, at nine of the clock.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of botches, of or about the Privities.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of diachilon magnum ℥ i. of Tile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oyle ℥ ſ. or of the oyle of Galbanum, or of the oile of Ammoniacum. Mixe theſe and make a maturative unguent for the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nereall Botch; which being opened, heale it with a ſtiptick Plaiſter. The dyet where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by bits are ſet down for the Palat, ought not ſo preciſely to be preſcribed, as Noſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Doctors have cunningly invented lawes for women that lie in: They may eat reaſonably, and drink a draught of wine ſometimes, and their meats may pretty well be ſeaſoned with ſalt, according as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the diſeaſe is.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:119881:27"/>
                  <head>The cure of Leproſie, and of Tinea.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the water of Baulme, of Speedwell, of Betonie, of Mugwort, of Fumitorie, of Succorie, ana ℥ ſs. of the liquor of Microcoſme, of Camphorated Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, ana ℥ i ſs. of the oyle of Juniper Berries, of Bayes, ana gut. v. in which you are to diſſolve, of the flowers of Caſſia newly drawn ℥ iij. of Calabrin Manna ℥ ſs. and adde thereto the Syrup of Stae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>has <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> vi. of our Myſterium gr. i. Mingle theſe, and make a Paleſtine Potion, which muſt be taken by the Patient, faſting daily in the Bath, and this alone is ſufficient to cure a Lentigo.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Bath is made thus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the roots and green Herbes of Balatrachium, of Flammula (Flavel) <hi>M.</hi> x. of Colts-foot <hi>M.</hi> v. of artificiall hot-Bath. as much as is enough. Make a Bath, let the Leper make uſe of it as long, till all the impure excrementitious ſcurfs are gone from the body. He may be dipped after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the tub (chaire) of the heavenly water, or the <hi>Indian</hi> Bath.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:119881:28"/>
                  <head>The cure of a deform'd skin, running o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e with a ſtrange colour: for all manner of ill effects of hairs, and how they are to be mended.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of diſtill'd Wine <abbr>lb</abbr> i ſs. of the white of boyled Egs num. x or xii. of the calx of Eg ſhels ℥ vi. of burnt Tartar, of alu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men plumoſum vel ſciſſum, of Salgemmae, ana quart i. Diſtill theſe into a water, adde thereunto of the roots Polygonum ℥ ii. of Aſphodel, of Brionie, of white Lillies, ana ℥ i. of Aaron ℥ i ſs. of the greater Comfry quart i. of the Herbe of Flammula <hi>M.</hi> iii. of Leviſticum <hi>M.</hi> i. of flowers of Beanes, of Lilium convallium, ana <hi>M.</hi> ii. Diſtill theſe again, and adde thereunto of the water of young cut veines that are cut <abbr>
                        <hi>lb</hi>
                     </abbr> ſs. of Honey quart i. of Camphore ℥ ſs. of leaves of Gold <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of the filings of Pewter, of Lead, of Copper, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of the Solar and Lunar Markaſite, of Chimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lea, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. Let theſe be macerated for a moneth in Horſe-dung, ſtraine and diſtill it, then make a Bath of the tincture, to be uſed outwardly, or let the haire be waſh'd
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119881:28"/>with it for a fortnight, put of Camphore to it <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. and the party may uſe the Paleſtine Potion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To cure the ſcabs.</head>
                  <p>AT the firſt entring into the Bath, and at the comming out of it, let the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie drink a diaphoretick potion, and ſo let him uſe the <hi>Indian</hi> Bath for a ſennight. Then let him take off the <hi>Indian</hi> Bath, <abbr>lb</abbr> i. of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troleum ℥ iii. of the Philoſophick oyle ℥ i. Let theſe be boiled, well luted, the liquor being cooled, ſoak ſpunges in it, and ſo take it out, and afterward put it into the <hi>Indian</hi> Bath; and that alſo muſt be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for eight dayes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Against burnings and parts kill'd by froſt.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of cocted oyle of Nuts <abbr>lb</abbr> ſs. of Harts Suet, of Goats Suet, of oyle of yolkes of Egs, of Wax, ana quart i. Make an unguent, ſtill moiſten the ſore with it.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:119881:29"/>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Against Varices, when the Arteries or Muſcles are ſwell'd and look black.</head>
                  <p>PHlebotomie muſt be uſed, after that the places affected muſt be anointed with mans greaſe diſtill'd for ſeverall weeks.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> venemous contagious diſeaſes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of Sydericum decocted in old <hi>Alſatian</hi> Wine ℥ v. of ſyrup of Lemons or Orenges ℥ i. of the liquor of camphora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Treacle ℥ ſs of the liquor of Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme, of the oyle of Turpentine, of Juni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Berries, ana gut. v. of red Corals <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs. of the ſpecies's of Gemms ℈ i. of the Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian earth, gr. v. of the beſt Unicorne, gr. iii. of the beſt Moſch, gr. i. of orientall Saffron, gr. iii. of our Myſterium gr. i ſ. Mix theſe and make a diaphoretick potion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The cure of St <hi>Antonies</hi> ſire.</head>
                  <p>EVery yeare, the Sinews, Muſcles, Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries on the legs and feet muſt be beaten, then this following Medicament muſt be miniſtred.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:119881:29"/>
                  <p>℞. Of the juice of Tartar gut. x. of the water of Arſemart ℥ iii. of our Myſterium gr. i. Make a potion of it: at laſt dip a lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloth into the hot liquor, apply it fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to Antonies fire; which is:</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the pouder of red Myrrhe, of white Frankincenſe tyed in a bag, ana ℥ ſs. of very ſharp Vinegar <abbr>lb</abbr> i. of Tart, or Aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick wine <abbr>lb</abbr> ii. Let theſe be boiled.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The cure of Impoſthumes.</head>
                  <p>SOme Impoſt humes are ſimple and mild, others are malignant. For the malignant Impoſthume, beſide the uſe of Chirurgicall meanes, this following potion may be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of our Myſterium gr. i. of the juice of Tartar gut. x. of oyle of Turpentine ℈ ſs. of Juniper oyle, gut. v. of the liquor of Camphorated Treacle <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs. of water of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leriana, of Fumitorie, of Veronica, ana ℥ ſ. Mingle theſe and make a potion; inwardly muſt be uſed a Medicament, which openeth the exulceration, eſpecially of the Carbun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle or Anthrax, or the peſtilentiall boyle.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the Cryſtallin Realgar ℈ i. of Calx vive <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of Oak miſleto, a ſufficient
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119881:30"/>quantitie. Make an aperitive unguent of it. Afterward in the very ſame manner, as uſually is proceeded with a ſimple Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthume, let there be applyed a concocting and attractive medicament, vulgarly a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turative joyned with an attractive.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the juice of the herb of March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mallows, of Dwarf Elder, of Coleworts, of Rue, of Oxylapathum, of Arſeſmart, ana ℥ ſ. of Muſcilages, of Linſeed, of Fenugreek, of Pſylium, of Quinces, of Colophone, of the Miſleto of the fir or pine tree, of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, of the tops of the Larix (the lark tree,) of Juniper, of the root of the great Cumfry, ana ℥ i. of Bdellium <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> vi. of Figs, of Raiſins boyled, ana ℥ i. of Beanes, ana ℥ ſ. of the powder of Rhubarbe <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of the root of Hermodactyls <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of Citrin Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ℥ ſ. of Foxes and Cats greaſe, ana ℥ i ſ. of womans milk <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iii. of Tyle oyle <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iii. of Juniper oyle, of Dill oyle, of chamomill oyle, of ſweet Almond-oyle, of the oyle of the yolks of Egs, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i ſ. Make a ſuppu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating Plaiſter according to Art, then with a ſtiptick plaiſter, cicatrice it: Phlebotomie may be uſed alſo in this caſe.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:119881:30"/>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The cure of Ulcers.</head>
                  <p>IN the firſt place, to aſſwage the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous paine of Ulcers, as of Gangreen, Cancer, and the running Phagedena, and the like, with a Balſame or a nodyne Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent, this following Chironick potion is to be given thrice in a day.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of Swallow-wort, of the herbes of Wintergreen, of the leſter Centorie, ana <hi>Mi</hi> i. of the Auguſtan Dragon, of the midler Cumfry, of Arſeſmart, ana <hi>M</hi> ii. of Celan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine <hi>M</hi> i ſ. Boyle theſe in a Kettle for an houre and a halfe, luting the junctures ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, ſtraine it with Beer, new Wine or new Meale, and preſſe it out.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of this expreſſion ℥ iii. of the water of the Cervin germination <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. and diſſolve therein of granated Manna ℥ i. Then adde of Rubarbe extracted with ſpirit of Tartar ℈ i. Mix theſe and make a potion.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of this expreſſion ℥ iii. of Nater of Palma Chriſti buds ℥ ii. of the oyle of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niper Berries, gut. v. of our Myſterium gr. i. Mix theſe and make a potion; if there be any neceſſity, that there muſt be applyed a cauſtick Medicament to the hard and callous
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119881:31"/>mouthes of Herpes, aſtiomenum, the wolf (as triviall Doctors would have it) then once or twice there muſt be uſed that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing one.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the oyle of fix'd Arſenick, of burnt Allom quencht in Vinegar, in lieu of this prepared Chalcanthum (vitriol) ana ℥ ſ. Mixe theſe and make an unguent; Or,</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the Oile of fixed Arſenick, of of the juyce of Celandine, ana ℥ ii. ſs Boile away the juyce, and adde of the Oyle of Gloves, ℥ ii. of the Criſtallin Realgar, ℥ ſs. Mixe theſe, dip a linnen cloth into it and apply it, and guard the affected place about with a Repelling Medicament, (vulgarly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Repercuſſive and Defenſive Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) namely, with a warme Decoction of Oeſipus or lana Succida, (the fett of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waſhed wooll) which is a defence and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection againſt increaſing ſymptomes: For the ripening of the ſcurvie, and for the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out the foundation of corrupt fleſh, apply this following.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the unguent of Ceruſe, ℥ ſs. Of Tile-oile, <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of Harts ſuet, of Crude But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i ſs Mix theſe, then apply a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Unguent (called Mundificative) to the Ulcer, which is made thus:</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:119881:31"/>
                  <p>℞. Of Turpentine boiled in the ſtrongeſt red Wine, and boiled away, and in water of Arſeſmart, or Celandine waſhed nine times, or in Miſleto of the Pine-tree ℥ iiil. of yolks of eggs, num. x. of crude honey <abbr>lb</abbr> ſs. of Aloes waſh'd in water, of Cyclamen, or Plantaine ℥ i. of Calcined Alome, often quenched in Vinegar ℥ i. ſs. of aes viride, ℥ ſs. of Vitriol Chalcanth, ℥ vi. Boile theſe into a browne Unguent.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of this Unguent, quart i. of oyle of Mercurie <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. Mix theſe and uſe it: but if the bones be eaten by rottenneſſe, if the fleſh be black and dead, or if any part or member be quite and abſolute dead, then let it be taken off by one inſtrument or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the next place to it bee guarded thus:</p>
                  <p>℞. Of Oyle of Cloves, made of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phore by the white of Eggs, ana ℥ ſs. Mix theſe, and binde a Stiptick Plaiſter to the place affected, which muſt be continued ſo long till all be covered with fleſh: at laſt the Ulcer is to be healed with the following Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick plaiſter.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of Virgin wax, of gold Lethargyr, ana <abbr>lb</abbr> i. of Colophonium, of Calmy, ana ℥ ii ſ. of Sallet-oile, <abbr>lb</abbr> i. ſ. of Opopanax,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119881:32"/>of Sagapenum, of Bdellium, of Ammonia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum of Galbanum diſſolved in Vinegar, ana ℥ i ſ. of the true bloud ſtone, of red Corals, of Sarda, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> v. i. of Mum, of Maſtix, of Myrrhe, of Frankincenſe, any ℥ i. of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Antimonie, ℥ ſ. of Crocus Martis <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of the Reſine of the Lark-tree, ℥ ii. ſ. Let theſe be boiled according to Art into a plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and ſoftned with the oile of Hyperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, or earth-worms.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt ſtubborne <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers, which will not eaſily cloſe, by reaſon of rotten fleſh, and other defects.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of calcined Sal armonic and Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, as much as you pleaſe, ſublime it; take out this ſublimate, and cleanſe it, and ſublime it againe together with the feces. Being ſublimed and purified, ſet it in a glaſs in a Cellar, let it diſſolve; annoint theſe Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers with a Feather dipped into the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, and lay on them a Stiptick Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:119881:32"/>
                  <head>To heale a wound.</head>
                  <p>IT is found by experience, that care muſt had, that the lips of a wound muſt bee wiped, and well annointed, bones broken well ſet, or being out of joynt, be put in their right places, and the wound alſo be filled with warme Unguent; if the wound be on the head, the Medicament muſt be laid on ſilke, becauſe of the tenderneſſe, (noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the skin of the Brain, or <hi>Pia mater</hi>) and our warme Oile, or the oile of Juniper Berries) be ſyringed into every corner, and the Fractures or Luxations thereof be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed with it, round about the wound where the Medicament of the place affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed are, muſt be made wet with the warme decoction of the greaſie wool, to keep off any other ſymptomes or defluxion falling that way; and that muſt be done twice a day for eight dayes together, or nine, that it be firme enough, provided that alwayes the wound be waſhed at the firſt dayes with a Cerotick Laver.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:119881:33"/>
                  <head>A Vulneraris <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the green Herbs of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winckle, of Arſeſmart, of the yellow Comfrie, of Ophiogloſſon, (Lingua Serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taria,) of Plantaine, ana m. i. of the roots of the great Comfrey, ℥ vi. of Ariſtolochia rotunda <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iii. Let theſe be beaten to a Pap, putting a little quantitie of wine to it, boile it for ten houres, like a Chironick Potion, being ſufficiently boiled, then beat it very well, ſtraine it through a cloth, to that ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned liquor put of cruce honey, or in lieu of it of May butter, Crude <abbr>lb</abbr> i. of the ſlime of Earth-worms ℥ v. of Harts marrow ℥ iii. of our Mumy quart i. of Fuſed ſalt, of Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Martis, of the flowers of aes viride, ana ℥ ſ. of Citrin Amber ℥ i. Let theſe be boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led alſo, and be ſtrained through a cloth preſſe it, then ſet it in the ſun or Horſe-dung to digeſt it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Our vulnerarie is made thus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the oyle preſt from ſeeds of Hypericon, of our Turpentine, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſme, of the larix (larke trec) ana <abbr>lb</abbr> i. of the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119881:33"/>beſt red wine <abbr>lb</abbr> i. Let theſe be boyled for an houre, then add to it of freſh ſallet oyle quart i. of the beſt red wine <abbr>lb</abbr> i ſs. Let theſe boyle again for an houre, then add to it of the flowers of Hypericon, of Prunella, of the leſſer Centorie, of the beſt red wine a ſufficient quantity. Let it be boyled againe for ſix houres, that the wine be boyled away, at laſt put to it of Maſtix, of Myrrhe, of Frankincenſe, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i ſs. of Mumie <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iii. Let theſe be digeſted for a moneth at the Sun, or longer; then take a feather, dip it into the Balſame, and anoint the wound with it, and apply a ſtiptick plaiſter, that no veines, arteries, nerves, or other liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may appeare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Our vulnerarie Balſame is this.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of Turpentine oyle <abbr>lb</abbr> ſs. of Tile-oyle quart i. of flowers of Hype<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricon, of the leſſer Centorie, of the yellow Comfry, ana a ſufficient quantitie for to fill it up. Let theſe be digeſted at the Sun for ſix dayes, and preſſe it, afterward put other flowers to it, for to digeſt them, and that muſt be iterated ſeven times. Then adde thereunto of waſht Turpentine ℥ vi. Digeſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119881:34"/>it againe. If any thing of the blow remaine in the wounded part, which the Medicine could not get out or heale, as of the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, be it of an Arrow, or a Bullet, gotten into the cloſures, or hollowneſſes of the bones, under the skull, or the concavities of the eyes, the ſame muſt be gotten out by a ſpell. If any bones be looſe, or ſplinters, or the like of the weapon be left in deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate wounds, then apply the following plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in lieu of a common ſtiptick plaiſter.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of wax <abbr>lb</abbr> i. of the juice of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtan Dragon <abbr>lb</abbr> ſs. of Colophonie, of Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers wax or Raſom quart i. of gumme Ammoniac ℥ ii. of yellow Amber ℥ iii. Make a plaiſter according to art, which muſt be tempered with the oyle of yolks of egs, then let the wound be bound or dreſt onely, with an ordinarie ſtiptick plaiſter, and ſo cicatrize it. Provided that by al means the chyronicall potion be adminiſtred.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Medico-chymicall curation, of the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſickneſſe.</head>
                  <p>THE beſt antidote (praeſervative) is the moſt excent eſſence of mans blood, by whoſe meanes is procured, that the violent
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119881:34"/>influence of the Lunar courſe, ſhall never cauſe any Lunatick or falling ſickneſſe, or prevaile with ſuch a partie any more. This antidote is prepared in this manner.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of Mans blood which is yet hot ℥ vi. of diſtill'd wine ℥ i. Digeſt theſe for forty dayes in a body, then diſtill it in a Balmy, and ſeparate by a ſpeciall manuall the white liquor from the yellow. One ſcruple of this being given at the beginning of the New Moon, in the firſt fit, doth ſo operate, that it allayeth the fervent fury of the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſickneſſe, and the partie will never be troubled with that Epilepticall concuſſion. In like maner that glorious oyle of Cranium humanum, taketh away wholly and radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally the falling ſickneſſe, if but three grains be taken of it, and the party will never be invaded with it, and that oyle is prepared in this manner.</p>
                  <p>℞. A Mans skull, which never was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terr'd, and be freed from all moiſture (hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor) beat it very ſmall, force it ſtrongly by a great fire, in a retort, drive all its moiſture over into the Receiver, which liquor muſt be put againe on the feces, and be driven over againe; and being iterated a third time, then is this oyle of mans skull elixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119881:35"/>or brought to a perfection, which muſt be kept ſafe in a glaſſe for uſe: it is a moſt precious treaſure.</p>
                  <p>There are other myſteries hidden in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Animals, as in the Elk, Kite, Bees, which in the ſame manner cure for ever Epileptick convulſion: But I paſſe them by to avoid prolixity.</p>
                  <p>There is uſed alſo againſt the falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; to the party are given nine graines of reverberated Antimonie, when the firſt Paroxiſme is upon the patient: If the fit comes again, then muſt be conveyed into the party ten and eight graines, an houre af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fit is over, then nine graines againe, if another fit comes, after the third Parox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme be over, the party will be troubled no more with it.</p>
                  <p>A third meanes is Linterium; to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty muſt be given an houre before the fit commeth one Scruple of the liquor of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phirizum or gold, and three houres after the fit, take a ſcruple, and that muſt be uſed a ſixth time, if the Epileptick fits continue, afterwards the partie will be quite rid of it.</p>
                  <p>The laſt meanes is a moſt cleare tincture of red Corals, at the firſt fit muſt be given
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119881:35"/>to the partie halfe a dram, and as often as the fit returneth, then this doſe muſt be continued, and cureth this diſeaſe fully.</p>
                  <p>I paſſe by here by thoſe moſt excellent ſecrets of Gemms, as of Smaragd, of Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, of Garnat, of Turquois, which being uſed, are of the ſame energie, and ſuffer no returnes of the falling ſickneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Hitherto have we handled of the foure Phylacteries, or Olympick myſteries. Now we will come to the Euporiſtick Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and will ſpeak of an exact Method, being grounded upon a long experimentall knowledge. In the firſt place, to take away the cauſes of the falling ſickneſſe, and to keep off its returnes: The party is to be purged with three graines of black Sneez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, being taken either in ſmall Metheglin, or in a decoction of Hypogloſſon (tong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort,) being ſeaſoned with ſpices. Its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration is thus:</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the root of black Hellebor, which beares purple flowers, being freſh and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous muſt be cut, ſprinkle it or poure on it the aethereall eſsence of wine, diſtill it, the firſt muſt be gentle, then increaſe it by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, let all the liquor be drawn over; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ſeparate the celeſtiall eſsence of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119881:36"/>wine by a gentle fire in a balmy, from the black liquor, in the liquor which remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the bottome of body or glaſs, muſt be diſsolved Sugar Candy as much as is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: Thus our Helleborine is prepared.</p>
                  <p>After the body is purged, there muſt be miniſtred the oyle of Vitriol, being redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into a volatile eſsence, which fully cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Epileptick diſtention, and bringeth the body to the priſtin goodneſs: Which if it be not wanting, then make the olympick cret thus:</p>
                  <p>℞. Of Hungarie Vitriol <abbr>lb</abbr> xii. of Spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium Electum, of Camphore, ana ℥ v. poure on theſe three the water of Paeonie ſeeds, gathered at the decreaſe of the Moon, and let theſe be driven by a Chymick deſcent, even unto red feces.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of theſe red Feces <abbr>lb</abbr> i. of diſtill'd li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor <abbr>lb</abbr> ii. of eſsence of wine, of water of Celandine, Baulm, of Germander, of Valeriana, of Plantaine, ana ℥ i ſs. Let theſe be diſtill'd with a ſtrong fire in a glaſſe retort: then:</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the red Feces <abbr>lb</abbr> ii. of diſtill'd li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor <abbr>lb</abbr> i. Let theſe firſt be ſteep'd, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſtill it day and night, then commeth over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ogether the phlegme, ſpirit and oyle, which
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119881:36"/>are thus ſeparated: The phlegme is ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a Balmy, the Spirit by a Seraphicum, and the red oyle in an Athanor. Of the phlegme is given to yong people before the fit commeth, to Aged people is given of the Spirit one Scruple; to old people is given of the oyle gr iii.</p>
                  <p>That is none of the meaneſt Antidotes againſt the falling ſickneſs, which is taught in the Stechomantia, uſed by ſome of the <hi>Sabaeans.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>℞. Of the waters of the root of Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhade, of Winter-Cherries, of the ſeeds of Paeonie, gathered in the wane of the Moon, ana ℥ ii ſ. of freſh Caſtoreum <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of the ſpecies of Diamoſchum dulce <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i ſ. of Virgin Hony <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Anacardin Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. Let theſe be diſtill'd in a Balmy, to which muſt be added, of prepared Pearles <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of the ſhavings of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corn gr. iiii. of the ſimple oyle of Vitriol. gut. v. of Anis ſeed oyle gr. ix. Mixe theſe: adminiſter <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i of this liquor before the fit commeth, let it be iterated for nine daies together, then this horrible diſeaſe will be abſolutely cured, though the party had been afflicted with it xx yeares.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:119881:37"/>
                  <p>More Antiodtes can be found out for the Epilepſie by him that knoweth (indeed Phyſitians that will be perfect, ought to know) the Aſtronomical Arts, among which is numbred the <hi>Magia Teurgica, Cabala Aegyptiaca, Necromantica Orientalis, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racteriſticall</hi> impreſſion or ſpels the Coeleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Sophia, and others, not convenient to be inſerted here.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:119881:37"/>
               <head>The Pyricall Art for Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinall Salts prepared Chymically; By D. <hi>George Phaedron,</hi> that Famous PHYSITIAN.</head>
               <head type="sub">How the Plague, that Epidomicall Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe, is cured.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the cauſes and ſigns are conveyed into mens bodies, as it were with one fall, as daily experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſheweth, and is taught by, or in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>topyrick Art, ſo that by reaſon of your nimble and ſodaine quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of deſtroying can hardly be allayed, here in this place, beſides the ordinary method obſerved in cures, care ought to be had, by
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119881:38"/>wiſe and diligent &amp; induſtrious Phyſitians, that the comming and creeping poiſon be expeil'd preſently from the more principall members, by ſpeciall and ſingular Antidotes; which are had againſt the horrible infection in the art call'd Orientall Charontick, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racteriſtick impreſſion, the perfect medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, the Coeleſtiall Sophie, and other Arts belonging to Mathematicks. And that I might not be contrarie in the cure of the Plague, which divine Science was impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto me, naturally being inclined, or by force of Nature in Aſtronomicall Arts, and will in few words ſet down, as much as time will permit, the ſeverall cures of the ſaid Arts, what their efficacy is againſt this diſeaſe. And in the firſt place the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rientall Charontica witneſſeth to be known among the <hi>Tharſi, Alexandrini,</hi> and in our age, that the following purge, being taken at the beginning of the infection in caſe of neceſſity, never miſs'd, ſo that for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in this manner might be prepared in ſhops for a ſovereign medicine.</p>
               <p>℞. Of Euphorbium ℥ i. of the beſt Myrrhe, Of the Maſculine Frankincenſe <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacanth ℥ ſs. Incloſe theſe in browne Crude bread, let it be cocted in the Oven, this ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119881:38"/>matter being cold, adde thereunto of red Corals, of Tranſparent Citrin Amber, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs. of Unicorn horn gr i. of the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baic Opium ℈ ſs. of the beſt Moſch gr. iii. of Orientall Saſtron ℈ ſs. Make a maſſe of Pils in ſublimed Wine, according unto Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Diambra. If the partie be of twenty yeares of age, let him take of it <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. or ℈ ii. if the partie be younger, then a leſſe quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity will ſerve; and if the party be ſtricken in yeares, then a greater quantitie muſt be taken. The partie muſt faſt for five houres after the taking, and the parties ſtomack being ſomewhat recovered, let him take the following potion.</p>
               <p>℞. Of Philonium Perſicum, or of the beſt Treacle ℈ i. of the Spices of Gemms ℈ ſ. of red Corals <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of red wine, in which Crude ſteel is quenched ℥ ii. of the water of Prunella, of Baulm, ana ℥ ſ. Make a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which expels the Plague, Pleuriſie, Flux, Inflammation of the throat, and other mortall diſeaſes, curing them radically, not ſuffering them to returne, according to the antient experience of the orientall Charon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick.</p>
               <p>Secondly the Characteriſticall impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, before other Medicaments propounds
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119881:39"/>this Electuarie, one dram being by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient taken ſeveral times, and well covered, expels that deadly poiſon wonderfully by ſweat and Urine, if well prepared by a good Apothecarie, it will not faile in curing the peſt.</p>
               <p>℞. Of Rhubarb ponticum, of Zedoaria, of Dictamn. Creticus, of Elicampane, of Angelica, of Cardopatia, of Magiſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, of Valeriana, of Gentiana, of Morſus diaboli, of Tormentilla, of Pimpinella, of Biſtorta, of Doronicus, of Ariſtolochia longa, of the herbe of Paris, of Swallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, of the leaves of Scordium, of Cardu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Benedictus, of Rue, of Sage, of Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, of the herbe of Paris, of Cardiaca, of Hypogloſtum, of Cordiall Flowers, of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary flowers, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of Bayberries, of the Herbe of Paris, ana ℥ ſ. of Juniper Berries <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iii. of the ſhavings of Nuces Vomicae <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of Aniſe-ſeed, of Fennell ſeed, of prepared Coriander, of Ocimum, of Citrum, of Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, of Sorrell, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of Ants egs, living under Pinetrees ℥ ſ. of ſhaven Liquorice, ℥ i ſ. of Lignum Aloes <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i ſ. of Opium The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baicum <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Myrrhe, of Frankincenſe, of Maſtix, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iii. of Ginger, of Galanga, of Cinamom, of Mace, of Nutmeg, of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119881:39"/>Cloves ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Long Pepper, of a grain of Paradiſe, ana ℈ iiii. of old red wine <abbr>lb</abbr> ſ. of ſcumm'd white honey <abbr>lb</abbr> ii ſ. of Roſe Sugar <abbr>lb</abbr> i ſ. make an Electuarie.</p>
               <p>℞. Of this Electuarie, of ſyrup of Citrum, ana <abbr>lb</abbr> i. of Aquavitae thrice diſtill'd <abbr>lb</abbr> v. Let theſe be infuſed and ſtand in horſe dung for a moneth, then diſtill it gently in a Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
               <p>℞. Of this liquor ℥ i. of the ſyrup of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus ℥ i. of Vinegar ℥ ſ. of Roſe water ℥ i ſ. of Ants egs which are under pine trees <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of dry berries of the herbe of Paris num. iii. of Cordiall ſpecies of Gemms ℈ ii. of the horn of the Unicorn, or of harts horne, caſt at the firſt breed gr. iii. of gold leaves n. i. of Saffrongr. iii. of Camphore gr. i. Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle it for a potion.</p>
               <p>The poiſon being expelled, let the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties linnen be either burnt or flung into the River with his urine. This purging Electu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary being taken, let the contagion be what it will, the partie infected will finde eaſe and help; Phlebotomie is not to be uſed, being dangerous, and other waies made uſe of by Moderne Phyſitians.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the Perfecta Medicina for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling of the Plague, the following Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119881:40"/>is much commended and of great effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie, to be made by an expert Chymiſt.</p>
               <p>℞. Of yellow Sulphur ℥ x. of Myrrhe, of Frankincenſe, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> vi. of Aloes waſht nine times in water, of Prunella ℥ i. of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Vitriol, of prepared Salt, ana ℥ iii ſ. Mix theſe well, ſublime the Sulphur, and this ſublimate muſt with freſh ſpecies's mixed be ſublimed again, which if iterated the third time, then you have an excellent Balſame.</p>
               <p>℞. Of this Balfame <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of Myrrhe, of Frankincenſe, of Auſtrian Saſtron gr. iii. of the Syrup of Citrus ℥ i. of Baulm water ℥ ii. Mixe it.</p>
               <p>This potion being taken daily preſerveth and cureth the Peſt, without any other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament, cureth the deſperate Pleuriſie, all manner of Coughs and corruptions of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane bodies, expelling them more then is credited. But if the heavenly ſoule and fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vertue be drawn from this Balſame, it is of a moſt noble quality againſt outward and inward diſeaſes, which is much to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed by a Phyſitian: For this Myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am is reduced into a more excellent Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cament, a mighty treaſure for all manner of men (diſeaſed) which I ſpeake of now, in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119881:40"/>this envious, covetous, and proud Age. Laſtly, the Coeleſtiall Sophie affords a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous heavenly Treacle, which expels any Venome from mans body. Chymically it is prepared thus.</p>
               <p>℞. Of a part of mans body, cut ſmall, of old and pure Sallet oyle, ana <abbr>lb</abbr> i ſ. Let it ſtand in putrefaction in hot horſe dung for a Moneth, then diſtill it in a retort: After this diſtill'd liquor of <abbr>lb</abbr> i. adde of old Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridate ℥ v. of Alexandrin Treacle ℥ iii. of the moſt fragrant Moſch <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ. of Amber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greaſe <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. Mix theſe and let it ſtand in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion for a moneth in hot horſe dung, then diſtill it in a Balmy, then is your Coeleſtiall Treacle prepared.</p>
               <p>℞. Of the liquor of this Treacle <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of Sorell ſyrup ſimplex. of Lemon juice, ana ℥ i ſ. mix theſe. This potion muſt be given three times to the partie, every fifth houre, if any boyle appeareth outwardly, bring it to maturity, and then open it; together with this potion and other Medicaments the olympick plaiſter, or our wonderfull ſtichicum.</p>
               <p>℞. Of the juice of the root of the herb of Paris, of Angelica, of Atiſtolochia rotunda, of Aſarum, of the greater Comfry, of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laria,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119881:41"/>of the herbes of Betonie, of Prunel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ls, of the leſſer Centorie, of Perſicaria, of Celandine, of Pyrola, of Agrimonie, of Plantaine, ana ℥ i of Muſcilage, of Linſeed, of Fenugreek, of March-mallows, ana ℥ i ſs. of white wax <abbr>lb</abbr> ſs. of Colophonie ℥ ii ſs. of Pitch, of Raſom, ana ℥ iii. of Sallet oyle <abbr>lb</abbr> i ſs. of Turpentine, waſht nine times in water of Solatrum ℥ iii. of Opopanax, of Serapinum, of Ammoniacum, of Galba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num diſſolved. in Roſe-water, ana ℥ i ſs. of Citrin Amber, of Maſtix, of Myrrhe, of Frankinenſe, of Aloes waſht nine times in Roſe water, ana ℥ i. of Styrax, of Sperma Ceti, of Terra Sigillata, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Rhubarb, of Rhaponticum, of Calamus Aromaticus, of Zinziber, of Acrons, ana ℥ ſs. of the ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Peacock feathers, of Snake skins, ana <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Antimonie ℥ ſs. of red Corals, of white Corals, ana ℥ i. of Lethargyre <abbr>lb</abbr> ſs. of Lapis Calaminaris ℥ ii ſs. of Haematires ℥ iſ. of Magnet ℥ iii. of Camphor ℥ ſ. of the oyle of Hypericon, of Chamomill, of Anethum, of Bayes, of Juniper Berries, of Egs, of Earth worms, ana ℥ i. of Spike <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of Harts marrow, of Capons greaſe, of Tithymal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, of Mans, ana ℥ i ſ. Boyle theſe to a plaiſter according to Art.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:119881:41"/>
               <p>Thus theſe four Mathematick Arts, teach us to cure Peſtilentiall diſeaſes, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomicall experience, aſtords no nobler thing among the ſimples, then the Magick ſtone, or Philoſophick; the ſoule of rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berated Antimonie, the diaphoretick liquor of Ophirizum, the oyle of Pearles, the tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Gemms; theſe alone are held the higheſt and onely <hi>Magnalia.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The leſſer Surgerie of <hi>George Phaeàron</hi> that famous Phyſitian.</head>
               <p>VVHereas in our age from the hands of Phyſitians, Surgery is faln upon Barbers and Bathmen of no experience, the foure principall parts of Phyſick, Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, Chimiſtry, and Mathematick. The love unto my neighbour hath moved me, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a long experimentall knowledge, to ſhew an eaſier and ſafer way, very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient and ſafe for all ſtudents in Surgerie, not checking my Conſcience for the doeing of it.</p>
               <p>Therefore I will preſcribe briefly and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuouſly the kowledge of all open ſores and ulcers, how theſe methodically may be
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119881:42"/>cured phyſically and ſpiritually, which not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Symptome being diſcovered, which daily moleſteth mankinde, the good of the univerſall Chriſtendome, chiefly of the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious principalitie of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> be promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, where when I was a ſtudent in Arts, and was a practitioner, I was courteouſly dealt withall, by all manner of perſons.</p>
               <p>There is propoſed in our protopyrick Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cina, &amp; in our daily practiſe, a threefold kind of open ſores, w<hi rend="sup">ht</hi> a cure belonging therunto.</p>
               <p>Firſt that which is hot, red, and is found about the nervous parts and paſſages. And that is cured with the Vincetoxicum.</p>
               <p>The other ſort is burning, cauſing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme paines, without any redneſts, or in parts full of nerves. And that is cured by Centaurium Minus.</p>
               <p>The third and laſt, is accompanied with a perpetuall tumor and running, this we cure with Pyrola. Thus:</p>
               <p>℞. Of this herbe M. v. or of the root ℥ iii. put in <abbr>lb</abbr> iii of clear and old wine, or in pure fountaine water in a clean pot, lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the junctures well, ſet it in boyling wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, let it ſtay there for halfe or a whole houre, let one moitie be boyled away.</p>
               <p>℞. Of this water ℥ iii. with an ounce
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119881:42"/>of Canarie Sugar diſſolved in Cinamon wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to be given to the partie affected, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the judging of the diſeaſe, being an ordinary cuſtome among wounded men, in what part ſoever of the body the Symptome be, the cure muſt be begun from within, and the efficacy of the inwardly taken Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine is felt; the wound muſt be waſh'd with wine, in which is boyled the herb Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolz, or the plaiſter of the powder of Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rola muſt be applyed: The powder and Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter may be omitted, that the wound may be cured with one onely thing.</p>
               <p>But in the venereall diſeaſe, if application be made in the ſame way, among the herbes there is none more effectuall then is Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gloſſum, which prevaileth more, then may be done by anointing, fumigation, or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing meanes; and effecteth thus much, that none of the diſeaſed curſeth either Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon or Phyſitian.</p>
               <p>And becauſe theſe three kinds, by reaſon of mixed ſignes are hardly diſcern'd or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh'd; therefore we may ſafely take our courſe to the preparation of the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction.</p>
               <p>℞. Of Vincetoxicum, of Centaurium Minus, of Pyrola, of Hypogloſſum, ana M ii.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119881:43"/>boyle theſe after our way: The Surgeon will be eaſed of his daily labours, and will help the partie in a ſodaine neceſſitie with the following wine.</p>
               <p>℞. Of Hypericon, of Veronica, of Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tago Utraque, of Betonie, of Eupatorium, of Prunella, of Vinca per Vinca, ana M i of Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rola Sylvatica, of the leſſer Centorie, ana M xvi. of the root of Swallow wort <abbr>lb</abbr>. ſs of of white Sanicle, of Ariſtolochia rotunda, of Sow bread, ana ℥ i ſs. put theſe herbes and rootes at the time of Vintage in a pipe of new wine, let it work together for three moneths, then take out the herbes, ſeparating the wine, put freſh herbes into, and for to make the Wine of an Aromatick Fragran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</p>
               <p>℞. Of Zinziber, of Calamus Aromaticus, of Cloves, ana ℥ i of Cinamon, of Mace, of Nutmegs, ana ℥ ſs. Put theſe into a bag, and put it into the fat. Thus you have in ſtore a medicinall wine outwardly to waſh the ſores, inwardly to be uſed for congluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating wounds and ulcers; the patients will commend their Surgeons for it, becauſe they furthered thereby their cure.</p>
               <p>But if a Surgeon be more induſtrious for to make a more happy cure, by a chymicall
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119881:43"/>Art of a moſt excellent uſe, he may extract the eſſence from Imperatoria, which is of a moſt excellent healing vertue. Imperatoria being well purg'd, and being beaten with a good deal of the whiteſt bread, being put into a hogs bladder, well ſhut and tyed, ſet deep in horſe dung weekly, or at the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day looking to it, when it lookes like purple Meath, then preſſe it out in a preſſe: the remainder muſt be digeſted againe, and then be preſt out againe.</p>
               <p>This viſcous liquor is put in a body and digeſted in the Balmy for ten daies, at laſt diſtill it in aſhes, the oyle and water comes over through the Helmet. Theſe ſeparate in a Balmy, with a gentle fire, then the phlegme cometh over, the eſsence of impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratoria remaineth in the bottom like an oyle. Halfe an ounce of it and one ſcruple of ſalt, and three ounces of the beſt wine, with a decoction of any vulnerarie water or juice of Plantaine, being taken mornings and evenings, according as occaſion ſerveth, and the neceſſity of the diſeaſe requireth, it healeth more, and agglurinateth all manner of freſh and old ſores, then may be well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsd in a great volume, purging by ſweat, urine, ſtool bleeding, and an inſenſible tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:119881:44"/>
               <p>That ſingular Arcanum is to be prefer'd alſo of Oculi Cancrorum, which by Pyrick Art for daily uſe, may be made thus: Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſe ſubtilly the Oculi Cancrorum, being calcined muſt be ſet for a moneth with the eſſence of wine in a Balmy; ſtill it oven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrongly ſix times, at laſt the oyle muſt be ſeparated from the eſſence of wine a ſixth time in a Balmy. One ſcruple of this oyle, with a dram of Treacle, or inſtill'd water of Fumitorie, muſt be taken mornings and evenings, according to the condition of the diſeaſe, which expels all contrary things to Nature, by the mouth of the wound, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by running, bleeding, or other effect, not leaving the ſumptome till it be cured and conglutinated. Another nobler Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is a Myſterium of the eſſence of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, the antient Philoſophers call'd it <hi>Ignis Adeptus,</hi> or <hi>Aqua Phlegetontica;</hi> which the Chymiſt prepareth thus:</p>
               <p>℞. Dregs of wine, or Tartar calcined in a reverberatorie <abbr>lb</abbr> iii. imbibe it with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd vinegar, putrify it for ſeven dayes in a Balmy, diſtill it as an Aquavitae in an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then retort (body;) at laſt put a ſtrong fire under it, a black liquor comes over with the wine, which muſt be ſeparated in a Balmy;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119881:44"/>the remaining feces muſt be calcined again for 24 houres in a reverberatorie, and muſt be imbibed againe as formerly with diſtill'd wine, this worke muſt be iterated as often, that all the tartareous ſubſtance be found to be conſumed. Afterward thoſe rectified li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors muſt be exiccated, then imbibe it with oyle or ſpirit of Vitrioll, as formetly the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cined Vitrioll was, and muſt be ſeparated againe. One graine of this Medicine, with one dram of Mithridate ℥ i ſs of diſtill'd Succorie water, as the Patients condition requireth, often taken, extinguiſheth the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall and prime cauſe of the diſeaſe, not a cicatrice will be ſeen, if any impure matter be left behind.</p>
               <p>Here would be briefly demonſtrated the true reaſon, whereby many could attaine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the higheſt Medicine of Vulcan Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſis, and the tincture of fixed Gemms by the help of the oyle Thion, but by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Philoſophick fire, and of the infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall waters immenſe ſecrets, the laſineſs, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice and vaine honour of this age is not to be edg'd on.</p>
               <p>At laſt there are moſt excellent univerſals in Medicina, as the diaphoretick liquor of Ophirizon, that the ſoluble oyle of Sol, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119881:45"/>tincture of the red Corals, which in like manner penetrate the whole body, and bring all open and gaping ſores and exulce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations to their priſtine integrity and health; as is ſufficiently made manifeſt in out coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall Medicina.</p>
               <p>Hitherto we treated of Phyſical curations, now followeth that we treat of the Heavenly, which we divide into a ſpecificall and characteriſticall.</p>
               <p>The ſpecificall is, which among vegetables ſheweth admirable effects, by a heavenly vertue of the firnament, affected with our body by a ſtrong impreſſion, without any preparation, ſeparation or auction; but is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd by God into theſe earthly bodies, by meanes of aſtrall infiuence; therefore they ought to be applyed, as they are naked before our eyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hydropiper</hi> hath received a marvelous quality by the heavenly influence, which if it be green drawn through a running water, and is laid to an open wound, no longer then one may be eating of an egg, being evapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in hot flints, and put into the earth and that be done in v. x. xv. dayes, as theſe herbes ſucceſſively putrify, ſo the wound in that ſpace of time healeth, and 18 cured, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119881:45"/>no impediment behind. Though the wound or ulcer muſt be kept clean from all impurity, after theſe herbes are buried, however for a ſpeedier healing, inward and outward medicaments are to be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred; of which hath been ſpoken.</p>
               <p>By a like magnetick operation, <hi>Solidago Minor,</hi> or <hi>Dracunculus</hi> doth its office, that theſe parts may not conglutinate and unite which Nature would have open; many at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to cure ſuch raſhly about the legs and feet with a fearful and dangerous limping or halting, who being forged by a timorous refuge, muſt take their inſtruction from theſe three plants, ſeeking for them in Fields and Acres. But if theſe herbes be dry, muſt be macerated in their own water, and muſt be applyed in that manner ſpoken of.</p>
               <p>This admirable potencie of the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the good God hath ſet before our eyes to be uſed for other deſperate diſeaſes, as it is apparent in <hi>Hypericon,</hi> which being gathered in its conſtellation, and uſed any way, is the greateſt Myſierium among the herbes, to expell Spectrums, Larves, and mad melancholy, whereby men many times fall into a phrenfie, madneſſe and deſpaire; among the Gemms, effect the ſame, the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119881:46"/>ſplendid red Corals; among the animall, the the blood of Pickerels is of the ſame effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</p>
               <p>In like manner amongſt herbes, is a moſt noble Medicament, which is called <hi>Syderi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> if its root be put in a glaſſe, full of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or wine, in which was hid any venome, breaketh it in pieces, but if the veſſell be of Pewter or of ſilver, the water or wine in it begins to boyle, riſeth and runneth out, nothing ſtayeth behind: Among Metals is <hi>Numus argenreus è Mercurio uòſtro confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus,</hi> being put to a diſh or drinking pot, doth the ſame: Among the Animals <hi>Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corxu verum</hi> doth the ſame, proved with a double black Taffety.</p>
               <p>The like aſtrall vertue to heale gaping fores or wounds, hath Symphitum Majus, the greater Comfry, which being drawn green through water, and applyed to the wound, to let it rot there, the rotten ones muſt be put away, and freſh applyed, healeth the wound wholly.</p>
               <p>Of the like praiſe and commendation are <hi>Althaea</hi> and <hi>Mereurialis,</hi> none of the herbs can be more wiſhed for, either by or of the patient, nor of the Phyſitian; I had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten experience of it made at <hi>Ratisbone</hi> the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119881:46"/>laſt veare, in deſperate and moſt incurable diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>This alſo is to be added, that alwaies as the Comfry was rotten, the ſalt extracted from that herbe, I diſſolved in its proper diſtill'd liquor, and purged the wound from the matier, and uſed the oyle of Symphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum alſo to anoint it withall, a freſh leafe drawn through cold water, applied it to the wound, proceeding with the reſt <hi>ut ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</hi> I made uſe alſo, if neceſſity required it, of the eſſence, of this herbe, ſeparating it by circulation in a Pellican, the doſe was one Scruple in ſtrong wine.</p>
               <p>Theſe vertues being joyned with thoſe of Phyſicall and Coeleſtiall things, never any inveterate and obſtinate open ſore or wound hath deceived my undertakings, eſpecially when I made uſe of <hi>Hydropi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore theſe Magnalia endewed with a Heavenly aſtrall influence, ought not to be contemn'd by any Surgeon. As Chameleo Niger being gathered in the time of the operating influence, bringing to the other health, ſtrength, and naturall vigour, beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by a Nymphidick reaſon to that, which reſpecteth its ſplendor, and ſo on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119881:47"/>which is the laſt refuge to bring the decaying ſterill ſtem of great houſes upon another line.</p>
               <p>I ſay nothing of the Magnetick Schmaragd, not of the Electrin Pyralis, of ſuch like mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous thing, never any that are in Stoecho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantin arts have written or publiſhed, which had not given a hint of this aſtrall influence. For all things have their prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated time, either of their riſing or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying,</p>
               <p>The Characteriſtick cure is this, which up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on words ſpoken, written or graven, exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth its naturall potencie, by the heavenly quality of the aſtrals and ſeverall influences, ſtanding in affinitie with our bodies, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of numbers, Geometricall figures, and other ſignifications of fingers. But I omit this laſt part of my propoſition, by reaſon of the great contempt of this ungratefull age, and its ſiniſter and raſh judgement, that I may not proſtitute theſe great benefits of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any ulcers and wounds by conſtellated words, into which is imprinted an influence by art. This I ſpeak experimentally, that ſeven words imprinted on a golden lamin, doth actually effect, which fals according to the expectation of the patient and Phyſitian; and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119881:47"/>many other conſtellated words of vulnerated men, being heard but of one wounded afar off, without any medicament is healed, in caſe abſent phyſitian doth but know the abſent pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and the cure can be perform'd a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred German miles off. Moreover in ſuch a cure more miraculous hidden myſteries are hid of the Patriarchs, and antient Prophets, and may be ſpoken of, theſe and ſuch like naturall ſecrets every perfect Phyſitian hath need to know them. For in caſe of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, what can commend and prefer a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian without any dammage of his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence more, then in the very moment of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>focation, by a meer ſpeaking of five words to help a patient, and to draw out the bones or eares without pain, ſticking to the throat? Here availe nothing, the Pharmacopolian itineraries, and the crooked inſtruments of Chyrurgeons, which little availe in any ſuch ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tanean caſe, becauſe alwaies things are made worſe when ſuch inſtruments were uſed, and the Patients are very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome eaſed, unleſſe preſently great and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved ſecrets be in readineſſe to be uſed. What better and pleaſanter thing can hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to a ſouldier, who is deſtitute of all hope and help, by the blow given to him in any
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119881:48"/>hour upon any aſtrall influence whatſoever, if by the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p of ſome conſtellated words ſpoken, any crooked arrow, or other ſhot, or beaten into his fleſh, to take it out with two fingers by the place it went in? Here is no need of cauteries or pyroteries appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated for capacities fitted, the weapon muſt be drawn forth freely; neither is there any need here of ſection, or rather butcherie, the piece of the weapon muſt not be turned, nor muſt the weapon that is in the fleſh be cut or broken in pieces. What ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh more a travelling man, if any bullet had been ſhot into his bladder, to get it out without paine, by ſome ſpell laid upon? Away with that tyrannicall manuall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtigation of Chyrurgeons; about which many of the Patients, either fall into ſwoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding under their hands, or die quite out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right. What nobler thing can be had in ſtanching of Bleeding or the running of the glutinous humors call'd Sinovia, where the totall vertue of the bodie groweth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective, then when a wiſe Phyſitian with one word wearing about his neck, without any hurt or application of any other medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caments doth ſtay it? Thus all ſuch deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate diſeaſes are cured by a characteriſtick
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119881:48"/>way being endowed with a celeſtiall and aſtrall inflowing qualitie, which Arts by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ignorance of ſome, and the contempt of ſome fooliſh Phyſitians, lie hid in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and theſe blaſphemous Alaſtors, will rather detract the honour from God in theſe high and miraculous operations of Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteriſtick cures, and attribute them to a bad intention, then to God who is the only ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall cauſe thereof. By reaſon of their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence, I omit this Characteriſticall Art, to ſpeak of ſuch motions and commotions, neither will I make mention any more of the firſt <hi>Adams</hi> antient Philoſophie, gotten by <hi>Semhamaphor of Rhaziell,</hi> whereby man may by a divine meanes, get and attaine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all, what ever his minde may deſire. For whoever is a true and ſerious lover and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of truth, he may finde about me theſe Megaleia and ſecrets at <hi>Ingolſtad;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I have made ſeverall experiments in the preſence of great Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs, and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Perſons, and deſire theſe and other writings of mine to be made approved to all ſuch which wiſh well unto me, upon paine of my body, honour, and the loſſe of my goods.</p>
               <p>And thus much ſpoken of the phyſicall
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119881:49"/>and heavenly cure of all ſores, ulcers and wounds, to be begun by the center, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching Chyrurgeons, that walk on the true way, to accept of this my faithfull work for the promoting of Gods honour, and the good of the neighbour; and thus I pray they may conſtrue it, till I bring forth greater and clearer matters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:119881:49"/>
               <head>The Chymicall Furnace OF <hi>GEORGE PHAEDRO.</hi> Which containeth the Compoſitions of the chiefeſt Secrets.</head>
               <p>GOld is broken in its Metalline Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and malleableneſſe by water of Salt: and this water is made by a ſanguincous diſtilling, without addition. It is a naturall ſalt, which wee dayly uſe at our meales. This water of Salt is waſhed from the Gold by ſweet raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water: The ſame alſo is diſtilled to the higheſt degree, then the tincture of Gold is detracted from the body by ſpirit of Wine.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119881:50"/>this is made meerly of Wine, without any other addition: and the ſpirit of Wine is made again out of Wine, without any other addition. This is abſtracted againe from Gold, and thus the Gold without any addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is graduated into a volatility, ſo that it may be brought into a liquor; in this manner is made alſo the Liquor of Corals, Pearles, and others, as alſo of Silver. And ſo there is nothing added unto ſuch Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, but Salt, Wine, and Water: but not a potent Water, as ſome Chymiſts and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts make.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Eſſence of Wine and of Herbes, from which are made Aquavitae's.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the beſt red wine or Spaniſh wine <abbr>lb</abbr> viii. macerate it in a large Pellican, or Circulatorie in hot horſ-dung, for 2 months, or in a Balmy for thirty dayes; then there will ſwimme on the Phlegme an olagineous Liquor, which with a very gentle fire in a Violl muſt be ſo long ſeparated coldly, till that tender and pure fatneſſe, or the vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſpirit of Wine come no more diſtilling from the Alembick; digeſt that again in
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119881:50"/>a Balmy for xxx dayes. Then you have <abbr>lb</abbr> i. of Wine, one ſcruple of the Eſſence, the true Elixir for the prolonging of life. From that may be made golden Water, or Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitae: if Plants and Spices mixed with ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Wine be macerated for a Philoſophick time; as, Melitena, Celandine, Elleborus, Roſemarie, together with Cloves, Ginger, Cinamom, Nutmegs, and the like. If you proceed in this manner in the drawing of the Eſſence out of one pound of Hydropi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, you will get two ſeruples of the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
                  <p>There is anther more compendious way to diſtill by a Balmy and cold Water, with an Alembick, whoſe receiver hath a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble neck.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Liquor of Ophirizum.</head>
                  <p>THe Liquor of Ophirizum, among other Secrets, is an univerſall medicine ſo powerfull, that it defends the whole body, and being corrupted, reſtoreth it to former health: And is made thus; Ophirizum by the regall Cement, or Antimonie Lamin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> muſt be diſſolved in the green Liquor of ſalt into a powder, which afterward muſt be
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119881:51"/>waſhed in a diſtilled Coeleſtiall Water, to get off all its ſaltneſſe: or if you will proceed more nimbly, cement the Lamins of Ophirizum, together with Lamins of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, covered for xxiv houres, then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyne them, then is your Solar Calx prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Then upon the waſhed powder, or purged Calx poure ſpirit of Wine, that it ſtand over it ſix fingers breadths, and the junctures being well luted, macerate them in a Balmy for xx or xxx dayes; then poure forth the Citrin Liquor, leaving in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome a moſt Candid powder, and ſeparate the ſpirit of Wine very ſubtilly in a Balmy, from the yellow Liquor of Ophirizum.</p>
                  <p>At laſt the extracted colour of gold muſt be five times driven in a Retort, then is your quinteſſence of Sol, or the potable gold, perfect, whoſe gr. iii. are given in aqua Dracunculi. This Liquor of Ophirizum maketh the ſpirit of Wine as dead, alive, increaſeth the radicall Humidum, and ſo corroborateth the whole body, that nothing goeth beyond it. This Liquor, I ſay, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the pores, and nimbly penetrateth all the parts of the body, rectifieth the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted bloud, conſumeth ſuperfluous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and confirmeth or ſtrengtheneth
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119881:51"/>univerſally all the Faculties and their Funi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: Laſtly, by the benefit of this Oph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizum, to ſpeak by particular of it, every intemperateneſs is cured, even Obſtruction, Phlegmon, Tumor, Putredo, Impoſtume, Fever, Peſt, Madneſſe, Falling-ſickneſs, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poplexie, the Palſie in any part of the body, Defluxions, ſhortneſs of breath, Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Pleuriſie, trembling of the Heart, Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, corruptneſs of the Liver, of the Spleen, the Scirrhus-arquatus, Malus-habitus, Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, the Cholick, the Iliack-paſſion, all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Fluxes, the Wormes, Hemerods, the ſtone of the Kidneys and Bladder, the viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Gonorrhes, Diabetes, Iſcheria, the Rupture, the Concurſe of Hyſterical ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes, the oppreſſion of the Moneth, and their immoderate flowing, the Whites, the riſing of the Mother, and the falling down of the womb, Sterility, all manner of Gouts, Chiragra, Gonagra, Iſchias or Sciatica, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephantia, or Leproſie, Venereall Infection, the bitings of venemous beaſts, the Anthrax, Cancer, ſmall Pox, Herpes Exedens, Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grene, Fiſtula, eating Ulcer. To ſpeak it in a word, the Liquor of Ophirizum expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and cureth radically all inward Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the body, and all outward ones, which
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119881:52"/>any other Medicament cannot cure by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their extream malignity; and the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall neceſſity, being Gods pleaſure, do not permit their cure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Oile of Pearles.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of prepared Pearles ℥ ii. of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled well purged vineger <abbr>lb</abbr> ſs. (in ſtead of vineger may be uſed ſpirit of wine, one quart of it.) Macerate it in a circulatorie for a moneth, then the pearles doe diſſolve into a ponderous juice, caſt off the reſt of the liquor. This whole diſſolved maſſe may be ſeparated <hi>per alembick,</hi> in the ſame way as the gold was. The doſe of the oyle of Pearles is gr. vi. which preſerveth the body in the ſame vigor of ill, reſtoreth the ſame to its former health; it hath not its fellow in curing of phrenſie, palſie in any part, the cramp, ſleepineſſe in old people, correcting and augmenting the milke in women, and in rectifying the ſeed, apoſtemes and eating ulcers, and hemerods.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:119881:52"/>
                  <head>The tincture of Corals.</head>
                  <p>POure ſpirit of wine on ſubtilly pulveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed red Corals, the ſpirit of wine muſt ſtand over them a hand-breadth, and the glaſſe beeing well luted muſt be macerated in hot horſedung for a moneth. Note, it muſt be driven ſix or ten times into a Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: but it may be prepared in a ſhorter way, namely, if once driven over, then let it macerate againe in horſe dung for a ſennight, ſo that it be macerated foure times in one moneth, and be driven foure times in open fire; afterward it muſt be diſtilled ten or ſixteen times according to Art. Then ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the ſpirit of wine in a Balmy, being poured on againe ſix times that ſpirit which is diſtilled, then is ſetled to the bottome a moſt red and cleare oyle of Corals. The doſe of it is one ſcruple, given in Succorie water, in good wine, or in a decoction of Chamae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drys. This ſoule I ſay, this pearle of Corals is one of the greateſt myſteries in Medicina, and is our moſt rareſt treaſure whereby radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally are cured all inward and outward ſymptomes, and the diſtempered body is reſtored to a perfect conſtitution. The quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119881:53"/>of Corals cureth in five weeks time all manner of convulſions in young and aged people, it ſtayeth any looſeneſſe, come it from what cauſe it will, in young and aged people, though it be come unto an extremity: it ſtancheth bloud in any part of the body, be it uſed any way: it ſtayeth the monethly courſes, and reduceth nature unto a good temper, and leaveth not matter for recourſe in the other parts of the body, as other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicaments uſually doe.</p>
                  <p>As the oyle of Corals is made, in the ſame manner is made alſo the oyle of Gemms, as of Smaragd, Rubie, Hyacinth, the ſtones of Garnets, Lycy, Cyanei <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The eſſence of Antimonie.</head>
                  <p>THere is great ſtore of Antimonie in mines of <hi>Germany,</hi> as at <hi>Tiohtelberg,</hi> ond at <hi>Plaun,</hi> a City in <hi>Bohemia;</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo about <hi>Maſſa</hi> is found ſome. The beſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timonie is found in <hi>Carinthia,</hi> and County of <hi>Tyral;</hi> where there are golden Mines. The yellow is of the beſt, the next is of a Saffron colour, and the third is blackiſh. This among other fruits of the water, hath as many ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and ſo good ones, that they ſcarce can
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119881:53"/>be expreſſed by man. It hath an inward efficacitie from the firſt Originall and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of things unto this day, and continued inviolably, neither hath the deluge ever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringed its native power, and ſtuck ſtifly to heavens influence to which it was inſlaved. Hence our moſt noble ſubject is reduced to its <hi>prima materia,</hi> ſo that the fire doth glitter every way like the Aether. It taketh away the cauſe of any diſeaſe, and tranaformes the impure body ſo, that is ſeemeth to want nothing of its moſt perfect health.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The manner of the making is thus.</head>
                  <p>ANtimonie well pulveriſed muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verberated for a moneth in a cloſed pot, and there breatheth forth a volatile flower which is of a white colour; then there commeth a yellow or citrin flower, after that there commeth a red and of a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple colour. Take of theſe red flowers two ounces, of rectifyed ſpirit of wine quart iii. macerate them for twelve daies in a circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Pellican, and ſeparate them in a balmy, the eſſence of Antimonie ſtayeth in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, which reneweth unto mans body all his ſtrength: The doſe of it is gr. iii. in
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119881:54"/>Baulm water, or Celandine water, or in good wine.</p>
                  <p>It cureth leproſie, and many other al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt incurable diſeaſes by inſenſibility; all diſeaſes are cured thereby radically, and whatever diſtempers the body, more then any other myſterious medicines, and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth Microcoſme to a moſt perfect health.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Arcanum of the Quinteſſence.</head>
                  <p>℞. Of ſulphur ℥ ſs. of ſpirit of Wine ℥xx circulate it for a moneth in the Sun, then diſtill it per alembick. Adde thereunto of Sulphur ℥ ſs. lute and macerate, and then diſtill it, out of theſe flowers you have Mumia terrae, and ſuch a Balſame, which preſerveth from putrefaction both alive and dead bodies, and protects them in that ſolidneſs, that no elementall corruption can hurt it. And for that reaſon the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame of Sulphur goeth beyond all other philoſophick tinctures. Its doſe is gr. v. in old white wine: And if you will make it more effectuall, then take the white flowers of Sulphur gr. i. of Antimonie ℥ i. of oyle of Gold ℥ ſs. of ſpirit of wine ℥ v. macerate it for a moneth, and bring it to a hard maſs: Its doſe is ℥ ſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:119881:54"/>
                  <head>Mercurius dulcis.</head>
                  <p>ARgent vive among metals is of a ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and admirable nature, containing a vertue of all the reſt: It is good againſt all manner of ulcers, purging the body ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically, reneweth the body, there is hardly any more eſtectuall myſterium, and is made thus. Firſt, Mercury is coagulated by common Allom water, and is ſubtilly pulve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed: Then abſtract from Mercury the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the white of egs from the moity of its calx, and bring it to a corallin colour: Its doſe is gr .iii. with treacle. The water of the white of egs is made thus: The white muſt be diſtill'd, and the ſhels of egs muſt be calcined, and the water of the white of egs is poured on the calcined ſhels; thus is your water of egs prepared.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Spirit of Vitriol.</head>
                  <p>THat kinde of ſalt, which the Greeks call <hi>Chalcanthum,</hi> and in Latine is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>atramentum metallorum,</hi> is ſeverall, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diverſity of Mines. Some of it is white, ſome is greeniſh, others is blew,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119881:55"/>mingled with red and yellow veines, and differ much one from another. In <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> it groweth, at <hi>Goſlar in Saxonie,</hi> at <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbach</hi> in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> at <hi>Smolnitz</hi> in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie,</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> in the Moſsan ground at <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſem agrum.</hi> In <hi>Cyprus</hi> the vitriol crude, the more it expels the wormes, or tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth iron into copper, the more uſefull is it in Medicina and Chymia. Moreover, the ſecret of <hi>Chalcanthum</hi> conſiſts of a tripple matter: The preparation of it is thus. <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canthum</hi> being driven with a vehement fire nine times, then forced in a retort, in an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanor kept for four daies and nights, then you have a moſt noble and moſt effectuall ſpirit. Then the Cholcothar from a red viol in like manner in an athanor for three dayes is diſtill'd with a forcible fire, and in the receiver you will have <abbr>lb</abbr> i. of Colco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thar, ℥ vi of red oyle. From the remainder is drawn the ſalt, which muſt be diſsolved foure or five times, and vaporated againe to a ſalt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:119881:55"/>
                  <head>Tartar.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of crude Tartar waſht in wine <abbr>lb</abbr> iii. and pulveriſe it, and according to the degrees of fire diſtill it like an aquafort, there commeth over a cleare liquor and a blackiſh juice, each of theſe muſt be diſtill'd apart in ſand foure times, the feces muſt be alwaies put away: at laſt for the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way its intollerable ſtink, it muſt be rectifyed ſubtilly in a Pellican, then you have a well prepared liquor of Tartar, which is of that efficacy, that it penetrateth all the body throughout.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, take of the aethereall eſsence of Wine, which in the circulation hath gotten a fragrancy ℥ x. of treacle ℥ v. of red Roman Myrrhe ℥ ii ſs. of Auſtrian Saffron, ℥ ſs. Mixe and diſtill theſe, then is your Treacle water prepared. For the making of the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantin Arcanum, take of ſpirit of Chalcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thum quart i. of the liquor of Tartar quart iii. Macerate theſe againe the philoſophick time: Its doſe is <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. to be taken in good wine. This is a divine Arcanum and Elixer, penetrateth the whole body inſenſibly, nimbly conſuming ſuch matters that are
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:119881:56"/>hurtfull unto the body, eſpecially if other peculiar things be added thereunto. If it be miniſtred for a moneth mornings and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, cureth the Gout, and the parts pained are to be annointed with this mixture.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of that liquor ℥ i. of Mumie quart i. Mix it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Philoſophick Salts.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the ſalt of Valeriana, of ſucco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, of Chamedris, ana ℥ i. of Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Vitriol <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. of common ſalt <abbr>lb</abbr> i. Mix theſe. Or;</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the ſalt of Vincetoxicum, of black Chameleon, of Celandine, ana ℥ i. of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſalt <abbr>lb</abbr> ſs. Mixe theſe. Or;</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the ſalt of Gold, of Antimony, of Melitena, ana ℥ ſs. of common ſalt <abbr>lb</abbr> ſs. Mix theſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Extract of Satyrion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the roots of Satyrion, cleanſe and beate them, temper them with a little quantity of the whiteſt bread, put it in a glaſſe and lute it, macerate it in warm horſe dung, take it out weekly, and when it
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119881:56"/>looketh like a red cremor, preſſe it ſtrongly very dry; add to the remainder more bread, macerate again, preſſe it, take out all the juice from it. This creme muſt be digeſted in a balmy for x daies, and then in aſhes diſtill'd, the phlegme and oyle muſt be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven over, which in a Balmy afterward muſt be ſeparated. The doſe of the oyle of Satyrion is ℥ ſ with one ſcruple of the ſalt of Melitena, and taken in good wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Mumy.</head>
                  <p>AS in the Macrocoſme things can be tranſmuted by ſome ſecret or other: So of Microcoſme, are things prepared which are very uſefull. The manner of it is</p>
                  <p>℞. Of rectifyed ſpirit of wine <abbr>lb</abbr> ſ. of the juice of Celandine, of Melitena, ana quart i. Circulate theſe in horſe dung for twelve daies, ſeparate them in a Balmy, and having macerated it again for a moneth, the Mumy being mixt with it, the Mumy muſt be diſlolv'd in it, ſeparate artificially in a Balmy Laſtly adde to ℥ vi of this liquor, oyle Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, of the Turks ſealed earth, of the oyle of Ophirizum, ana ℥ ſ. Circulate it againe for a moneth; then you have a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſmick
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119881:57"/>Treacle of Mumie, a moſt rare Myſterium, very effectuall againſt any poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Its doſe is <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſ.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Hermaphrodite.</head>
                  <p>IN Chymiſtrie is found by experience that the Hermaphrodite containeth all the vertue of the other Minerals; hence it muſt needs have a healing qualitie on mans body. Becauſe he is nothing then the eſſence of Minerals; if the Anatomie of Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme be conferr'd with Macrocoſme. Therefore the Hermaphrodite reſtoreth mans entire body, be it corrupted by what cauſe it will, to a moſt perfect ſymmetry, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that no perfecter medicine can be wiſh'd for to prolong the life in the a perfect health. The ſoul of Hermaphroditus is made thus.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of the Mercuriall eſsence of Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus. Vitriol, coagulate in its definite time of Philoſophers ſet, then ariſeth the ſaphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick flower of Hermaphrodite an admirable Myſterium of Macrocoſme. One part of it put into 3000 parts of diſsolved Ophirizum tranſmuteth all into its owne nature; one dram of this put to a thouſand drams
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119881:57"/>of Copper, tranſmuteth it into moſt pure gold. So one graine of the Hermaphro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite, and one ſcruple of Treacle taken now and then in good Wine, reſtoreth a diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered body to its priſtin and naturall conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution; and if you apply it outwardly unto any ſymptome, with diſtill'd water of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dropiper, it is more effectuall then any bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame, and cureth any ſymptome, ſooner then other Chirurgicall meanes. This Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maphrodite is the tincture known to thoſe that are buſied in the Chymick Monarchie, by name called the ſtone, its proper name is the aethereall Fire, involved infinitely in obſcure riddles.</p>
                  <p>I adde this alſo, out of <hi>Phaedro Agrippa,</hi> the Philoſophers Stone is a ſecret of ſecrets, if you wiſh for happineſſe, that you may obtaine the Philoſophers bleſſing; God li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth for ever. There is one object in the World for all, which properly is called of the Philoſophers; in the ſhell ſtayeth the white, which containeth the red: The one is called the male, the other the female, an animal, vegetable, and minerall: Its fellow is no where found, it hath an active and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive power, a dead and quick ſubſtance, a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Soule, which ignorant men hold it a
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119881:58"/>moſt vile thing, containeth in its boſome the foure Elements, found every where, commonly had by every one, is of a ſmall price; one pound is ſold for a ſhilling: It voluntarily aſcendeth, groweth black, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendeth and groweth white; increaſeth and decreaſeth; it is a thing which the earth produceth, and deſcendeth from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; groweth pale, and groweth red; it is born and dyeth, riſeth againe, and liveth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward; hath ſeverall wayes to goe to its end: Its proper decoction goeth beyond that of the fire; is ſlow, modeſt, ſtrong, and is augmented, and at laſt in a ſecure reſt is it rubifyed. This according to expectation, is called the Philoſophers Stone. Read, and read it againe, over and over, you will finde more plaine no where: If you are ſtill dull in your underſtanding, then are you not fit for this Art to learn it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How ſalt of Gemm, and the water of ſalt is prepared.</head>
                  <p>SAlt of Gemm, the pureſt of all, being ſubtilly pulveriſed, being put into a mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting pot, and ſet in a wind-oven, ſtanding in a gentle fire, let it ſtand on melting for three
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119881:58"/>houres, if the pot holdeth ſo long, let it cool of it ſelfe. Pulveriſe this, and ſet it in a pot againe into the Furnace; it muſt be iterated five or ſix times, and pulveriſe it ſtill. Take a quantity of the juice of Radiſhes, as much as the ſalt weigheth, put ſome of it in a wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den diſh grind it with a ſpoon; that which is diſſolved of the ſalt; thus hot, ſtraine it. and ſo go on with the reſt, and diſſolve all the ſalt in this juice, and ſtraine it: Coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late it, or diſtill the water from it; pulveriſe it againe, poure the diſtill'd water on it; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifie it in a Balmy for ſix daies and nights, ſeparate the water from it by diſtilling, let your firſt fire be gentle, as you uſually doe at the diſtilling of Aquafort, let all diſtill over, then encreaſe the fire, to calcine for an houre.</p>
                  <p>This warme Salt muſt be pulveriſed, and grinde it on a ſtone, let it diſſolve on a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Being diſsolved, ſet it in a Balmy to putrifie for three daies; then put it in a ſtrong body, diſtill it in Sand, uſe the degrees of fire according to Art. The remaining body being pulveriſed, muſt be diſsolved againe on a Marble, muſt be putrified as formerly, and diſtill'd a third time: The remainder muſt be very ſubtilly pulveriſed, put in a body,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119881:59"/>poure on it the three diſtill'd waters, let them putrifie for five daies and five nights, after this, diſtill it againe in groſſe Sand; at laſt let all come over through the Helmet, a Caput mort remaineth, which muſt be put away: But all the water for a day and a night to be putrified in Sand, which is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the ſubſtance of the Salt, then is to be diſtill'd per Alembicum. This putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and diſtilling muſt be iterated a third time, then you have the water of Salt. At the putrifying and diſtilling, the Veſsels muſt be well luted, that none of the Spirits get away.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The eſſence of Sol.</head>
                  <p>TAke Gold purged three times by Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, very tinnly laminated, or in its place, take fine Gold, put it in a bolt-head, poure on it the ſpirituall water of Salt, ſeale it Hermetically: Set it in digeſtion for foure or five daies, that they joyn, then open it, take off the neck in part, and ſet an Alem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick on it, lute it well, ſet it ſo long into Aſhes, apply a receiver, lute the glaſses jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures very well; diſtill it five or ſix times, and when it is cold, put the Gold and all the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:119881:59"/>matter in the body, into a jar glaſs; dulcifie it with diſtill'd raine-water from all its ſalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; the Gold remaineth in the bottom like a powder, for the Salt is not turn'd into the Golds ſubſtance. Poure Spirit of Wine on this Alcholiſed Gold, not a ſimple Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitae, ſtanding over the Gold ſix fingers deep, proportionably unto the Gold. Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifie it for a moneth in a Balmy, the Spirit of Wine drinketh the tincture of Gold, which muſt be put into another glaſs. For a further extraction, poure more Spirit of Wine on it a ſecond and third time, let all its tincture be extracted, the body of Sol re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth whitiſh and ſoule-leſs: At laſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate the Spirit of Wine in a Balmy, from the form Gold, and uſe it according to the manner you heard of.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A praecipitate of Sol.</head>
                  <p>IF you intend to prepare the praecipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate of Sol, then the Gold being dulcified with diſtill'd raine-water, and dryed, then proceed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:119881:60"/>
                  <head>Spirit of Wine.</head>
                  <p>TO make the true Spirit of Wine. Take a quantity of the ſtrongeſt Wine, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any mixture, be it white or red, the white is better, leaving leſs alcoll then the red, which runneth in no other form or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour then the white doth; cauſe it to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd like an Aquavitae, either in copper or glaſs, diſtilling coole. Taſte one drop or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if it commeth weak, then take off the receiver, apply a blind Helmet to it, of a good bigneſs, leſt the motion of the Spirits breake it if too narrow; ſet it on three foot, let it boyle for ten dayes. After you have opened, apply a head with a pipe, diſtill in a Balmy, and the Spirits come over. The manuall depends from theſe three. The glaſs with the wine muſt not ſtand too deep in the water, and the ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctures muſt be well luted to keep in the Spirits, and then the Spirit muſt not be mingled with the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Wine; which would eaſily happen, if the Balmy ſhould be made too hot. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obſerve the ſignes well: When little veines or drops appeare in the Alembick, then ceaſe, for the following is burning
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119881:60"/>Wine, and the receiver muſt be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Salt of Wine.</head>
                  <p>PRoceed as you heard, according to the firſt diſtilling, when all the ſtrength of the Wine is gone, then commeth the phlegm or wateriſh matter, let that be evaporated in a Kettle by boyling, or if you feare the Kettle to be endangered by the fire, put the matter into a narrower veſſell, and force it, there remaineth a yellow and impure ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which muſt be dryed, you have then a Tartar of a black colour, from which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very ſubtilly pulveriſed, and moſt ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly calcined, with a cole or wood fire, you can have the ſalt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Alcoliſed Spirit of Wine.</head>
                  <p>AND if you will have a moſt ſtrong<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and moſt fully graduated Spirit of Wine, for the opening and attracting of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and for gradation of formes, take of the Spirit of Wine as much as you pleaſe, diſſolve its ſalt in it, let it ſtand in digeſtion well luted for a naturall day, ſet it in Sand
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119881:61"/>or aſhes, obſerve the degrees of fire, apply a large receiver, poure the ſpirit on the ſalt againe, this ſalt muſt be calcined againe to a whiteneſſe, poure Spirit of Wine on it, and ſhake it, and diſtill it againe; weigh the Salt to ſee whether it loſt of its ponderoſity; if it be too much fix'd, then putrifie it in Spirit of Wine in a Balmy; laſtly, diſtill it ſo long, that all the ſalt be gone through the Alembick; and thus you have a Noble alco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſated Spirit.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The eſſence and forme of hearbes.</head>
                  <p>THere is drawn from flowers and hearbes a ſpecificall true property and colour, the body not being deſtroyed, as <hi>Theophrastus</hi> demonſtrateth in his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe <hi>de vita longa,</hi> and elſewhere: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the ſimples are put over night in the ſaid Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Wine; if you you will ſeparate, then doe it in a wet Balmy, the form like a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, remaineth in the bottom.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:119881:61"/>
                  <head>How the eſſence is drawn from hearbes.</head>
                  <p>ANY herbe being firſt beaten in a ſtone Morter, together with the flowers, leaves and roots to a pap, being well luted, muſt ſtand in digeſtion for a moneth in horſe-dung. Diſtill it dry in a Balmy; the remaining powder muſt be grinded upon a ſtone, and muſt be imbibed with its diſtill'd liquor, and digeſt it for a fortnight. After that let it be diſtill'd in aſhes, phlegme and oyle comes over together, which muſt be ſeparated aſunder, and the oyle muſt be ſafely kept. The remaining feces muſt be very ſubtilly pulveriſed, poure the phlegme on it, digeſt them for ten or twelve daies in horſe-dung, ſeparate the phlegme in ſand. The remaining black pouder muſt be albify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a reverberatorie, pouring on it its phlegme, and extract its ſalt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Diaphoretick Gold.</head>
                  <p>VVHich purgeth the blood, and the marrow in bones and the whole body. Draw the red colour from the red Mercurie, being prepared with the water of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:119881:62"/>eggs by the ſaid Spirit of Wine, as you heard above: Put an equall quantity of the ſoule of Gold, let it ſtand in putrefaction to be purged, then ſeparate the liquor from the Spirit of Wine: the doſe of it is gr. iij <hi>vel</hi> iiij. to be taken in Malmſey, for three daies together faſting. <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> ſaith, that this liquor cureth the Leproſie, contractures, and purgeth the blood mightily. More of this I ſpoke in the adminiſtration of <hi>Magna Chirurgia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of Mumy.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of well cut Mumy, put it into a Retort well luted, adding thereunto a like quantity of Sallet oyle for a moneth. the Retort being taken out, then cut ſome of the noſe of it, ſet it in ſand, lute a recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to it, and drive the ſtinking Mercury in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. Then ſet it in a place, where the people of the houſe may not be annoyed, into a Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my for five or ſix daies; thus the reſidue of the Mercurie will vapour away, in that warm Balmy. Cant of the liquor, the part indiſſolved is to be kept in the Balmy: Mixe with it ℥ vi of Treacle, of the beſt Moſch ℥ i. and keep it in the Balmy, or in hot aſhes in a Furnace for a month.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:119881:62"/>
                  <head>Turbith Minerale.</head>
                  <p>I had two waies to prepare the Minerall Turbith, firſt if the water of eggs from their calx be often digeſted and diſtill'd, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracteth its ſweet volatile ſalt, and by this evaſion it deſerved among the antients the name of <hi>Corroſivum dulee,</hi> mortifieth Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie, and rubifyeth like Corals, its digeſting and diſtilling being repeated: From this red Mercury can be drawn its eſſence by the Spirit of Vitriol, extracting it as long as the Spirit takes any tincture from it, which may be done at the xv or xvi iteration: The remaining Caput mort muſt be put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond way differs from the firſt. Put a ſtrong Aquafort upon two parts of tyle-meale, and adde one part of ſalt, diſtill it; the Aquafort will be as red as a Ruby, which muſt be abſtracted to a third part from Mercury by a ſtrong fire, and the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury muſt be grinded on the Marble twelve times, and then diſtill'd, being diſtill'd muſt be digeſted from its calx with water of egs, and being often diſtill'd, then your <hi>Turbith</hi> Minerall is prepared.</p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:119881:63"/>
                  <p>℞. Of this <hi>Turbith</hi> gr. v. Mixe it with one ounce of the juice of Roſes, to be taken before ſupper, mornings faſting gr. iiii. by night foure graines are to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. If it cauſeth any ſpume in the mouth, and the Patient fals into ſpawling, then adde to it, ſome-what of Vitrum of Antimony, or of its reverberated powder; then a gentle purging it will give. After that muſt be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the quantity of a Haſell nut of Theriaca Alexandrina, and make the Party ſweat. Theſe Patients may uſe alſo the following Gargariſme.</p>
                  <p>℞. Halfe a quartern of burning Wine, of Sugar candy ℥ i. ſmall pulveriſed, adde one ſpoonfull of the beſt Hony, mixe theſe and make a Gargariſme, as long as the <hi>Turbith</hi> is uſed, nothing ought to be applyed to the wound or ulcer, but this following plaiſter, neither ought it to be uſed above three times the <hi>Turbith,</hi> and its operation is to be waited for.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of Bdellium, of Serapium Colatum, ana ℥ i. of Frankincenſe, of Mumy, ana ℥ iii. of Wax <abbr>
                        <hi>lb</hi>
                     </abbr> i. of Colophonia ℥ vi. Make theſe to an Oppodeldoch, according to Art, it will purifie the more, if one dram of our <hi>Turbith</hi> Minerall be mingled.</p>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:119881:63"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Turbith</hi> Minerall being miniſtred with Spirit of Tartar, provoketh ſweating in the bed, and draweth pliſters and the like out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Alcool Vini.</head>
                  <p>ALcoliſated wine, Centrated Wine, Eſſentificated Wine with Alcool, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cool of Wine, Eſſatum Vinum, Eſſe vini is as much as Eſſentificatum: That is, when the eſſence of Wine comes over by diſtilling, then its phlegme remaineth in the bottom like the dregs of Honey; which if they have any Empyreuma or fierineſſe, the phlegme muſt be poured on again, and is to be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted till the phlegm be gone from the eſſence. Then poure the diſtill'd eſſence of wine on the phlegmes, and ſeparate it by diſtilling, which muſt be iterated ſo often, till the feces ſticking to the bottom be white glittering, which are <hi>Theophrastus</hi> his Alcool Vini, Sal Vini, or Vinum Alcoliſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:119881:64"/>
                  <head>Oleum Auri ſive Axungia.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THeophraſtus</hi> cals it Axungia, or butter of Sol, to be taken inwardly for the Fiſtula or Cancer, and outwardly to be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for an ointment: Its preparation is thus. Poure on the filings of gold, oyle of Maſtix, which having ſtood in digeſtion a moneth in horſe-dung, waſh it off from the oyle with warm water; let it ſtand again in digeſtion in Spirit of Wine for ten or twelve dayes, the Spirit being ſeparated, you find an oleaginous matter in the bottom, like unto butter. Take ſome drops of it at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, in a vehicle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Spirit of Tartar for ſweating.</head>
                  <p>LET the Tartar be well purg'd and waſht in Wine, dry it and pulv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>riſe it, put the glaſse with it into a wind-Furnace, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill per Alembic, as the oyle of Maſtix is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd, there comes over a thick matter, of colour and fragrancy like a Treacle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:119881:64"/>
                  <head>The oyle of Saturne and its Salt.</head>
                  <p>LEad in the firſt place is to be calcined, thus. Set a glaſed panne over the fire, put the lead into it, calcine it, ſtirring it with a ſpatule, at firſt it will look blackiſh, then yellow, at laſt it is of a red colour, pour di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd Vinegar on it, two fingers breadth ſtanding over it. Boyle it a little, when the ſcum riſeth, then toke it off the fire, and let it ſettle gently, and cant off the Vinegar into another pot, from the calcined Saturne. New Vinegar muſt be poured on the Lead, and this muſt be iterared as long as there is any ſweetneſs in the Lead. Theſe being done, let the gathered matter or a cetum be ſetled in the Balmy; let the Vinegar be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten off, there remaineth a ſweet Purple bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the bottom. To this matter, poure the Heavenly water, and let it boyle, it will caſt a white ſcum, which muſt be taken off, as long as there ariſeth any, caſt away the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining purple-dregs in the bottom. The off taken ſcum muſt be put in a Balmy, either to be vapored away or diſtill'd, it leaveth a dry and whitiſh body in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the glaſs, which muſt be diſsolved in
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:119881:65"/>ſome noble Aquafort, and be ſeparated three or foure times in a Balmy, where you will behold a faire diſsolution; on this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter poure againe the diſtill'd rain-water ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate the ſame in a Balmy, this muſt be ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated as long as there is left any acrimony of the Aquafort, you will ſee a white tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent matter, the true and ſweet ſalt of Saturn, being put into a Cellar, or any wet place, will diſsolve into a water or oyle, whereby outward and deſperate ſores or cancrous ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers are healed, and is an approved medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine.</p>
                  <p>Dr <hi>Daniell</hi> in his time, uſed only Lead di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſsolved in Aquafort, which he du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cified with fountaine water: An effectuall remedy <hi>ad ulcera Cacoethe,</hi> linnen being dipped into, and put into the places, uſing only the water, not medling with the powder of the Lead in the bottom.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The eſſence of Antimony.</head>
                  <p>CRude Antimony being reduced into a moſt ſubtile Alcool, put it into a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort, evaporate it in the degrees of reverbera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then ſeale it, and let it reverberate gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, provided it doe not melt. The venemour
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:119881:65"/>humor and Sulphur being evaporated, when it looks like a cinericious powder, then the middle degree of fire is to be uſed for eight or ten daies continually. Then uſe ſuch a degree of fire to it, that the Antimony look of a purple colour'd pouder. Take of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verberated Antimony ℥ ii. as much of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated Aquavitae, that it ſtand over it ſix fingers. Let it be digeſted in a well luted cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatory for twelve daies, then at the diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in a Balmy ſeparate it, then the Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitae will be tinged, which is the true eſſence of Antimony. The dead powder of it ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the bottom: Its doſe is <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. more or leſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The uſe of the eſſence or tincture of Antimony</head>
                  <p>THree graines of it taken in Wine, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Quartan, and all manner of Agues. Mr <hi>Thomas</hi> hath cured with it two Patients of the Dropſie, miniſtring two or three drops, mornings in white Wine; it giveth three or foure ſtools, penetrating and ſearching the whole body: It cauſeth a faintneſſe to the Members for an houre or upward, but after that, it reſtoreth ſtrength unto them; if there be any tumor within,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:119881:66"/>diſſolveth the ſame by ſweat and urine. It diſperſeth the Hydropick humour diapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retically. An excellent remedy for brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging down the Courſes, curing the jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Cholick. He uſed ſucceſsfully to boyes of three or foure yeares old; alſo the Quartane and Tertian Ague he proſperouſly cured with it. It is a rare medicine againſt the Venereall diſeaſe, cured foure ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients with it. He cured a woman with it which had the foule diſeaſe ſeventeen years, having had eleven ſuch tumours in the head, two in the arms; theſe were diſſolved only by the oyle of it. The tincture of Antimony is uſed againſt the venereall Itch and Scabs. The Patient ought not to come into the air, muſt be kept warm, and not walking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. He cured the Scropula, which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſeſt the whole Face; thus: He purged the Partie ſeverall times with Vitrum Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nii: after that, hee cauſed a decoction to be made of wine, in which was Vincetoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, both Centories, Sanicle, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Pyrola: The potion being ſtrained, he applyed the roots warm in bags, and thus did he reſtore that Patient.</p>
                  <p>He reſtored one Woman with the eſſence of Antimony, which was troubled with
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:119881:66"/>three and twenty open fores in her Legs, as reliques of the venereall diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Phaedro</hi> made uſe of Vitrum Antimonii twice on a moſt deſperate Hectick Feaver. He that maketh uſe of the eſſence or of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum of Antimony, let him avoid the aire.</p>
                  <p>He cured a Ploughman with Vitrum of Antimony, which was much moleſted with corroſions, expelling a great worm, 124 and little ones.</p>
                  <p>He cured another thus: He miniſtred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him ſixteen times of that Vitrum, who had two hundred holes between the Knee and the Knockle, purging him firſt downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, then by vomiting, taking away all the paines, only with calcined Vitrioll, and a mundificative unguent.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Phaedro</hi> hath cured alſo one that was troubled with the Gout, and another Woman, with the ſame Antimoniall eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, out of whoſe skull there grew ſcales. He cured alſo two deſperate Hectick Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and ſome that had the Quartan Ague. And ſo it cureth Impoſthumes, and malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant excreſcencies, worms, the Gout, vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reall paines and tumours, the Hectick Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and the quartan.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:119881:67"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> his <hi>Laudanum Opianum</hi> which he made uſe of againſt all manner of Agnes, as a Specificum.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>Phaedro</hi> his is this.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the beſt Opium Thehaicum, being cut <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Mumy gr. iii. of the juice of the root of Hyoſciamus <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. which muſt be gathered when Sol and Luna en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Libra,</hi> which is eight or five daies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore St <hi>Iohns</hi> day.</p>
                  <p>Put it into a glaffe, and digeſt at the Sun for fourteen daies, then is the Opium prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of Species of Diambra ℥ i ſs of Wine rectified five times <abbr>lb</abbr> i. Let theſe alſo be digeſted at the Sun for fourteen daies, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it daily three or foure times; then poure ſome red clear Wine on the prepared Opium, make it to a pap, and then digeſt it againe for three daies in the Sunne, being well ſtop'd, and then let it be exiccated. Then make it to a more thick maſſe on a Marble, with a little of the ſaid Wine, unto which you muſt adde of prepared red Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:119881:67"/>of prepared Citrin Amber, ana ℈ i. of the beſt Moſch or Amber gr. iii. of Camphore gr. vii. of orientall Saftron ℈ i. Let ſmall Pils be made of it, miniſter ſeven of them in <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. of Wine, to be ſwallowed; if the paine be vehement, miniſter vii about ſix of the clock, about nine, five, about foure of the clock, four of them to be taken in Wine. they admirably aſſwage all paines, and are miniſtred in all violent diſeaſes for to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and to heale.</p>
                  <p>Note, Laudanum alwaies doth its worke in ſix houres time, which maketh the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſleep for an houre; if there be any further uſe of it, then allow to its operation ſix houres.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The oyle of Realgar, or of Arſenick and its uſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of Realgar as much as you pleaſe, which is penderous and white, grinde it ſmall on a ſtone, adde to it purged Sal-niter, let it diſſolve on coales, the firſt fire muſt be gentle, that all venemous fumes may vapour away, and the matter of it be burnt. Being burn'd throughly, then increaſe the fire for foure or five houres, let the Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:119881:68"/>be like melting butter, all its vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous quality flyeth away, and a fix'd Real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar will be. Let it be in a Cellar on a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, diſtilling into a receiver, which is the fix'd oyle of Arſenic. Of this <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> made uſe of very much, it may be better rectified, as the oyle of Sol, if made in a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort, being poured on hot or heated Tiles. Outwardly Ulcers are anointed with all, and new Pocky ſores, twice or thrice at the moſt: it maketh them run as long as there is any cauſe for it; w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> cauſe being conſumed, the ulcer gets an Eſchara, which muſt be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed with the following butter of Sol, fals off, not leaving any mark or red ſpot. If any ſuch ſore is to be annointed with this oyle, then the next place or skin to it is to be anointed alſo.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Butter of Sol ad AEſcharum.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of freſh May butter, as much as you pleaſe, poure it boyling into water of Bean flowers, or the decoction of Lupini, Solomons ſeale. Quench it thus a third time, it will be very white and faire: Uſe it as you heard.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:119881:68"/>
                  <head>Aquila praecipitata.</head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>
                        <hi>1.</hi> The purgation of Vitriol.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the beſt blew Hungarian Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol ſixteen <abbr>lb.</abbr> put it into a glazed pot, poure on it cleare Fountaine or diſtill'd raine-water, boyle away a third part of it, filter or ſtraine it into a jar-glaſſe, ſet this ſtrained liquor into a moiſt ſand to cryſtalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, poure the water on againe, let it boile as formerly, iterate it ſo long as any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtals will ſhoot, then all its venemous qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is gone. In like manner let the pulveriſed Salt-Niter be diſsolv'd, and be purged, as you heard about the Vitriol.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Purgation of Sal Armonicke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>REcip.</hi> Of Sal Ammonick, of calcined Tartar, ana <abbr>lb</abbr> i. ſublime theſe twice or thrice in aſhes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:119881:69"/>
                     <head>Aquafort.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>REcip.</hi> Of the above prepared Vitriol, and rubified <abbr>lb</abbr> ii. of the above ſaid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Niter, and well exiccated at the Sun <abbr>lb</abbr> i. mix theſe being pulveriſed, diſtill gently at firſt, then increaſe your fire, let all the Spirits come over.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>
                        <hi>3.</hi> To purge this Aquafort.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>REcip.</hi> Of this Aquafort ℥ ii or ℥ ii ſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve it in the thinneſt Lamins of fine Lune <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii. which being diſolved, put it alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether into a glaſs; the feces of it being ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, cant off the water, let none of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter come after. Thus is the Aquafort purged. Of this Aquafort <abbr>lb</abbr> i. in which diſsolve one graine of the ſalt Ammonick, prepared afore, diſtill it gently in a Balmy, then you have the prepared Arcanum Regis, or T R.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:119881:69"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>4.</hi> Purgation of Mercury.</head>
                     <p>POure hot water on calx vive, ſhake it, coole and ſettle, filtrate the water, and diſtill it hot into Flint-aſhes, which if this be ſetled, then filter it. In this lie made of Calx vive, and aſhes of Flints, Mercury muſt be boyled a ſixth or ſeventh time, and that which boyleth away, muſt be applyed with freſh Lixivium. In like manner let Mercury be boyled a fourth time in ſalt and diſtill'd Vineger, ſo that the ſalt be covered with blackneſs, and the Vineger being evapora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, freſh Vineger to be poured on: At laſt let it be waſh'd a third time with hot wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and dryed, then it is fit for ſubliming, praecipitating, and for other buſineſses.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>
                        <hi>5.</hi> Purgation of Antimony.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>REcip.</hi> Of powder of Antimony, of purged Sal-Niter, of Calcined Tartar
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:119881:70"/>ana <abbr>lb</abbr> ſs. Melt it; thus melted, caſt it into horne, which being cold, take off the Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, it breaketh freely.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. ℞. Of Regulus of Antimony ℥ i. grind it ſmall, imbibe in a jar-glaſſe ſix times with Aqua Regis, diſſolve it in it, reſerve that which is diſſolved in hot aſhes.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. ℞. Of the beſt Gold, laminated very thinly ℥ ſs. diſſolve it apart in a jar-glaſſe in ℥ i. of Aqua Regis. Let it ſtand.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. ℞. Of purged Mercury ℥ iii. diſſolve it in a well luted glaſs body upon warm aſhes, pouring on it one pound of Aqua Regis. Put theſe three diſſolutions into a well luted cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curbit, ſtill it a ſixth or ſeventh time in hot ſand per Alembicum; that which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd muſt alwaies be put on againe. At laſt increaſe the fire, and let all come over. Then take out the remaining matter, and reduce
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:119881:70"/>it to an Alcohol on a ſtone, and reverberate it under a muffle, rule it with a gentle fire; the Mercury will look black, and then of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall colours. Continue the reverberation, and rubifye it, and let all the ſpirit of Aqua Regis be gone. Then waſh it with warm water, to take off all its ſaltneſs. Pulveriſe this Mercury well, poure on it of the beſt rectified ſpirit of Wine, let it ſtand over it three fingers; Standing in a warm place for three daies, and ſhake three times a day, then ſeparate it.</p>
                     <p>At laſt poure on the pulveriſed Mercury of the beſt diſtill'd Roſe-water, aromatized with Moſch, let it ſtand alſo in a warm place for three daies, ſhaking it thrice a day, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate gently unto a drineſs, it will be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cin praecipitated Aquila, alias, a purging mercurial eſsence.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>beds of Antimony.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, let the Tartar be well calcined, to acquire to it an acrimony; then let it be diſsolv'd in warme water. Poure out the water, the earth will ſettle to the bottom: If any acrimony ſhould yet be in the Tartar, then poure water on again, which being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:119881:71"/>muſt be put to the other; which muſt be continued as long as there is any acrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in it: Put away the dead earth. Theſe ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered waters muſt be boiled away, there remaineth a ſharp and fiery ſalt in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom.</p>
                  <p>℞. Of this ſalt ℥ iii. boile it in a pint of water, put to it of crude Antimony ℥ ſs. boile it well in a pann, as hard egs are boiled, and the water be clear: If the matter congea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, looking like a red gelly; put to it a ſufficient quantity of diſtill'd Vinegar, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Tartar and all malignity of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony from the redneſs, and diſsolve it. That redneſs of Antimony ſetleth to the bottom, Filter it is paper, the redneſs of Antimony abides about the Paper. Dulcifie this red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by pouring on warm water, and take off all ſuperfluous impurities, let it ſettle, the redneſs being on the bottome, ſeparate the water. Then exiccate on quick coales: its doſe is halfe a graine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:119881:71"/>
                  <head>Of the oyle of wax, which is like a Balſame in curing of wounds.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of new oderiferous wax <abbr>lb</abbr> ii. melt it in a pan gently, then put it into another veſsel fill'd with the beſt wine, and very hot, let it be cold, gather it with your hand, and preſs it hard, melt it again; and thus hot poure it in Wine, and thus doe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times. The laſt time being melted, add of tile-meal M. iii. Mingle it well being cool'd, put it in body with an Alembick, lute it well, that nothing may expire. The lute being dryed, ſet it in a ſand capel, make a gentle fire under it for nine or ten houres. At firſt there comes over a phlegmatick water of a citrin colour, when it hath done diſtilling, remove the receiver, keep the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin-water ſafe in a glaſs: Then apply a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother receiver to the Alembick, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the fire by degrees: At firſt the drops fall muddy, which being ſetled in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, congeale like butter, or a gelly. At laſt the following drops look of gold colour, which congeale not, but keep in a liquid ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. At the ſight hereof change your
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:119881:72"/>receiuer, that theſe golden drops be not mingled with the other, and muſt be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved apart. And this is the true oyle of wax, which keeps liquid for ay. Continue your diſtilling with the fire increaſed, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing fire muſt be kept for eighteen houres. At laſt more muddy drops will fall, which when you ſee it, then change your recever preſently to receive the feces, which are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid alſo.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A diſſolved Unicerne.</head>
                  <p>TAke prepared Pearles, poure on them Vineger, ſeven times diſtill'd our way, and diſsolve in hot aſhes. Abſtract after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Vineger in a Balmy, and if but few Pearles, put them in a jar-glaſs, and evaporate in warm aſhes, afterward p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ure on raine-water once diſtill'd, and evapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, continue it, till the water and ſowre taſt be gone. At laſt, diſsolve this powder of Pearles with rectifyed Spirit of Wine, and make uſe of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:119881:72"/>
                  <head>Acetum Philoſophorum.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip,</hi>
                     <abbr>lb</abbr> viii. of the beſt Vineger, diſtill <abbr>lb</abbr> iiii of it per Alembick; adde to theſe quart i. of purifyed Salniter, let the Salniter be well diſsolved in it, then diſtill in Sand ſtrongly, that the Spirit may aſcend and mixe with the Acetum. Take of this Ace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum as much as you will, add Bugloſs to it, call'd otherwiſe the herbe of Paris P v. put it in a violl, add to it well waſht Mercury P i. ſet it in digeſtion for xvi days or more, you ſhal ſee the effect. This Acetum diſsolveth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Narcotick and diaphoretick Antimony.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Of Antimony <abbr>lb</abbr> i. as much of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Sal-Peter, calcine it circularly in a high pot, increaſing the fire by degrees for three of foure houres; then calcine againe with Salniter, for ſome houres give a very ſtrong fire, that the pot be red hot. Take out the Antimony, beat it, diſsolve it in water, if any of the ſalt be left, filter and keep it back, and waſh it. Dry the remainder, and reverberate for ſome foure houres, then you have a very white powder: Its doſe is from gr. ii. to vii or ix. exceeding effectuall in Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian and Quartan Agues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:119881:73"/>
                  <head>Tartar.</head>
                  <p>THE liquor of Tartar and its Succus is thus ſeparated: The Tartar is waſhed ſeverall times in common warm water, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no impure dregs in it, at laſt it muſt be waſhed in warm Wine; it muſt be dryed at the Sun, and reduced to a powder, put it in a glaſse, lute it and diſtill in open fire; the junctures of the glaſses muſt be well guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the receiver muſt be very large. The firſt liquor that comes, is ſtinking, which is rectified in a cellar in wet ſand, and the ſuccus is rectified with diſtill'd Vineger in a retort in ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fire. Then draw it with the the Acetum, the drops come either red or citrin, according as the Tartar was, which in a funible muſt be ſeparated, and thus the Acetum receiveth the Empyreuma into the oyle, and the oyl ſucceedeth in a golden colour without any ſtink. Uſe:</p>
                  <p>℞. Of this Preparatum ℥ i of the volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble oyle of Vitriol ℥ iii. of aromatized Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitae, ℥ v.</p>
                  <p>Theſe, being mix'd, are circulated for a moneth; it is given in Wine <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>. i. or more, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the perſons condition.</p>
                  <p>Tartar cureth the Lues Venerea, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:119881:73"/>in guts, the riſing of the mother by ſweating, and all other evils.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Liquor of Tartar.</head>
                  <p>BEing given daily three times, is very good in the Palſy, it penetrateth the whole body, ſtrengtheneth the ſame, which ought to be in this diſeaſe. It cureth all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Jaundice, joined with the venereall diſeaſe. It rectifyeth monthly courſes; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth Leproſie at the beginning of it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken with oyle of Mercury cureth the Dropſie by Urine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Oyle of Dwarfe Elder.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REcip.</hi> Seeds of Ebulus well cleanſed <abbr>lb</abbr> iii or iiii, beate them well in a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, bringe all into a paſte, put it into a Ket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, adde a ſufficient quantity of River water to it, let it ſtand infuſed for 24 houres, then boyle it, let your firſt fire be gentle, and increaſe the fire by degrees, continue the boyling of it, that all the ſcum be gone: This ſcum muſt be gathered with a skimmer, and all the oyle ſwimming on it: All this you put into a long glaſſe, let it ſettle, thus warm
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:119881:74"/>for two or three daies, there appeareth a green tranſparent oyle, unctuous, ſetled to the bottom under that ſcum, and if the oyle doe not ſeparate well from the ſcum, then take it together, mingle it in warm water, let it boyle a little; afterward put it in a glaſſe, within few daies the oyle will ſettle, take off the ſcumm warily, and gather the ſetled green oyle, and ſet the ſcum apart, let it yeeld the oyle it hath among it. Uſe of this oyle a little quantity againſt all manner of paines cauſed by a cold diſtemper, in nervous ſymptomes and Arthritick paines. The manner of its uſe is: Take ſix or ſeven drops of this oyle, apply it warm'd to the place affected, then preſently the ſharp pains will be allaied.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:119881:74"/>
               <head>The judgement and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of Doctor <hi>GEORGE PHAEDRO</hi> of <hi>Rodoch,</hi> in ſome Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Medicaments.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>In the Herculean diſeaſe or Epilepſie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> uſed againſt this diſeaſe the ſweet oyle of Vitriol, <hi>per ſe</hi> without any other addition, very ſucceſſefully. For the Dropſie I uſed the rectifyed eſſence of Hellebore.</p>
                  <p>Againſt Conſumption, a diſſolutum of Pearles of the Indian oyſters.</p>
                  <p>Againſt the Stone I uſed the atereall juice of Cryſtals.</p>
                  <p>Againſt barrenneſſe, the red extract of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrium of Erithonzum.</p>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:119881:75"/>
                  <p>Againſt the venereall diſeaſe, the ſweet oile of Mercury. Againſt the Gout, <hi>Phaedro</hi> did uſe that excellent and noble Corallois, that is, the Chymicall Hermaphrodite, and took it three times inwardly, and cauſed himſelfe to be annointed with the rectifyed Spirit of Tartar, and made it penetrate: In a fortnights ſpace he was healed. He was then alſo troubled with a great ſwelling in his legs, accompianed with a fervent redneſſe. Againſt Cancer he uſed butter of Saturne, Againſt the Cramp and great Convulſions. He cured one, who was tormented with a running paine of his members, with a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple colour'd tumour joyned, running from one place into another, he uſed no other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament, then twice the ſanguin eſſence of Antimony. The Patient was recovered the fifth day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>In contractures and Conſumption.</head>
                  <p>FOR the expelling of theſe diſeaſes he miniſtred the ſweet diſſolution of Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme, miniſtring it inwardly ten times, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly he annointed the party with Bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers greaſe, mixed with the Philoſophers oyl. Theſe parties were cured within three weeks.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:119881:75"/>
                  <head>Against the Impoſthume in the head.</head>
                  <p>IN this occult diſeaſe, which puts the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian to great troubles, he gave to take of Ophirizum, which being taken, a Hiſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call obſtruction was opened, and the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſthume of the head broken; the patient was healed in a moneths time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt the Venereall diſeaſe and Pox.</head>
                  <p>ONE was moleſted with ſuch a Pocki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whoſe teeth were looſe, and troubled with great paines in the joints, the joints began to look black, full of ſcabs and contractures. He cured the party with the oyl of Mercury, mix'd with mans greaſe, and the oyle of Arceutides, with this every other day he annointed theſe Knots; and he annointed or rubb'd the teeth with the aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized Oleum Moſchocarium or of Mules. in fourteen dayes the party was recovered unto health.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:119881:76"/>
                  <head>Againſt the Dropſie.</head>
                  <p>VVHen I intended to cure this diſeaſe with Catarcticum Mercuriale, and to ſtrengthen the Patient, I reſtored the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient very well with diſtill'd water of Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mom, which came over in xxiv hours time, or the Diacubebe of Seplaſii, which was miniſtred in <hi>Rhois</hi> of the moſt vertuous and much praiſed eſsence of Gold in Wine of Pomegranates.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt the gripings and torments in the belly.</head>
                  <p>HE uſed the anodin Sulphur, of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trioll of Venus and Mars, reduced unto a more ſublime degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt the Jaundies.</head>
                  <p>IN this diſeaſe my Panchimagogum is of great efficacy, the extract of Rhubath, the Spirit of Tartar: The Stigian liquor: All which are ſingular myſteries for this diſeaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:119881:76"/>
                  <head>Againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers and open ſores.</head>
                  <p>THE ſweet oyle of Saturn, with Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phuncleum.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Againſt excreſcencies of the body.</head>
                  <p>AGainſt the great ſcales and excreſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the body, which attract to them almoſt all the alimentary, ſubſtance, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the body commeth into decay, he uſed the ointment o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>ilum of A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>um As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſtinum, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>chois, joyning thereto Chalcanthum, annointed, and tyed to the places.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
